{"Java":{"q71":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\n class Test implements Cloneable\n{\n    int a;\n\n    Test cloning()\n    {\n        try\n        {\n            return (Test) super.clone();\n        }\n        catch(CloneNotSupportedException e)\n        {\n            System.out.println(\"CloneNotSupportedException is caught\");\n            return this;\n        }\n    }\n}\n\nclass demo\n{\n\n    public static void main(String args[])\n    {\n        Test obj1 = new Test();\n        Test obj2;\n        obj1.a = 10;\n        obj2 = obj1.cloning();\n        obj2.a = 20;\n\n        System.out.println(\"obj1.a = \" + obj1.a);\n        System.out.println(\"obj2.a = \" + obj2.a);\n    }\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"obj1.a = 20\nobj2.a = 20","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"obj1.a = 10\nobj2.a = 20","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"obj1.a = 10\nobj2.a = 10"},"q70":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\n class Test\n{\n\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        String obj1 = new String(\"geeks\");\n        String obj2 = new String(\"geeks\");\n\n        if(obj1.hashCode() == obj2.hashCode())\n            System.out.println(\"hashCode of object1 is equal to object2\");\n\n        if(obj1 == obj2)\n            System.out.println(\"memory address of object1 is same as object2\");\n\n        if(obj1.equals(obj2))\n            System.out.println(\"value of object1 is equal to object2\");\n    }\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"hashCode of object1 is equal to object2\nmemory address of object1 is same as object2\nvalue of object1 is equal to object2","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"hashCode of object1 is equal to object2\nvalue of object1 is equal to object2","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"memory address of object1 is same as object2\nvalue of object1 is equal to object2"},"q73":{"question":"Output of follwoing Java program\n\nclass Main {\n public static void main(String args[]){\n   final int i;\n   i = 20;\n   System.out.println(i);\n }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Compiler Error","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"20","answer_d":"Garbage value","answer_c":"0"},"q72":{"question":"What is the use of final keyword in Java?","hint":"None","answer_b":"When a method is final, it can not be overridden.","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"When a class is made final, a sublcass of it can not be created.","answer_d":"All of the above","answer_c":"When a variable is final, it can be assigned value only once."},"q31":{"question":"Predict the output of following Java program\n\nclass T {\n  int t = 20;\n  T() {\n    t = 40;\n  }\n}\nclass Main {\n   public static void main(String args[]) {\n      T t1 = new T();\n      System.out.println(t1.t);\n   }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"40","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"20","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q75":{"question":"\nclass Base {\n  public final void show() {\n       System.out.println(\"Base::show() called\");\n    }\n}\nclass Derived extends Base {\n    public void show() {  \n       System.out.println(\"Derived::show() called\");\n    }\n}\npublic class Main {\n    public static void main(String[] args) {\n        Base b = new Derived();;\n        b.show();\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Base::show() called","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Derived::show() called","answer_d":"Exception","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q30":{"question":"Predict the output?\n\npackage main;\nclass T {\n  int t = 20;\n}\nclass Main {\n   public static void main(String args[]) {\n      T t1 = new T();\n      System.out.println(t1.t);\n   }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"0","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"20","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q74":{"question":"\nclass Main {\n public static void main(String args[]){\n    final int i;\n    i = 20;\n    i = 30;\n    System.out.println(i);\n }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Compiler Error","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"30","answer_d":"0","answer_c":"Garbage value"},"q33":{"question":"Is there any compiler error in the below Java program?\n\nclass Point {\n    int m_x, m_y; \n    public Point(int x, int y) {    m_x = x;    m_y = y;  }\n    public static void main(String args[]) \n    {\n      Point p = new Point();\n    }\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"No","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Yes","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q77":{"question":"Predict the output of following Java program. Assume that int is stored using 32 bits.\n\nclass Test {\n    public static void main(String args[])  {\n       int x = -1;  \n       System.out.println(x>>>29);  \n       System.out.println(x>>>30);  \n       System.out.println(x>>>31);  \n   }   \n} ","hint":"None","answer_b":"15\n7\n3","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"7\n3\n1","answer_d":"1\n1\n1","answer_c":"0\n0\n0"},"q32":{"question":"Which of the following is/are true about constructors in Java?\n\n\n1) Constructor name should be same as class name.\n2) If you don't define a constructor for a class, \n    a default parameterless constructor is automatically\n    created by the compiler. \n3) The default constructor calls super() and initializes all \n   instance variables to default value like 0, null.\n4) If we want to parent class constructor, it must be called in \n   first line of constructor.","hint":"None","answer_b":"1, 2","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"1","answer_d":"1, 2, 3 and 4","answer_c":"1, 2 and 3"},"q76":{"question":"Predict the output of following Java Program\n\nclass Test {\n    public static void main(String args[])  {\n       int x = -4;\n       System.out.println(x>>1);  \n       int y = 4;\n       System.out.println(y>>1);  \n    }   \n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"-2\n2","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Compiler Error: Operator >> cannot be applied to negative numbers","answer_d":"0\n2","answer_c":"2\n2"},"q35":{"question":"\nfinal class Complex {\n    private  double re,  im;\n    public Complex(double re, double im) {\n        this.re = re;\n        this.im = im;\n    }\n    Complex(Complex c)\n    {\n      System.out.println(\"Copy constructor called\");\n      re = c.re;\n      im = c.im;\n    }            \n    public String toString() {\n        return \"(\" + re + \" + \" + im + \"i)\";\n    }            \n}\nclass Main {\n    public static void main(String[] args) {\n        Complex c1 = new Complex(10, 15);\n        Complex c2 = new Complex(c1);    \n        Complex c3 = c1;  \n        System.out.println(c2);\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Copy constructor called\n(0.0 + 0.0i)","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Copy constructor called\n(10.0 + 15.0i)","answer_d":"(0.0 + 0.0i)","answer_c":"(10.0 + 15.0i)"},"q79":{"question":"\nclass Test {\n    public static void main(String args[])  {\n       System.out.println(10*20 + \"GeeksQuiz\");\n       System.out.println(\"GeeksQuiz\" + 10*20);\n   } \n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"200GeeksQuiz\nGeeksQuiz200","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"10*20GeeksQuiz\nGeeksQuiz10*20","answer_d":"1020GeeksQuiz\nGeeksQuiz220","answer_c":"200GeeksQuiz\nGeeksQuiz10*20"},"q34":{"question":"Output of following Java program\n\nclass Point {\n  int m_x, m_y;\n  \n  public Point(int x, int y) { m_x = x; m_y = y; }\n  public Point() { this(10, 10); }\n  public int getX() { return m_x; }\n  public int getY() { return m_y; }\n  \n  public static void main(String args[]) {\n    Point p = new Point();\n    System.out.println(p.getX());\n  }\n} ","hint":"None","answer_b":"0","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"10","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"compiler error"},"q78":{"question":"\nclass Test {\n    public static void main(String args[])  {\n       System.out.println(10  +  20 + \"GeeksQuiz\"); \n       System.out.println(\"GeeksQuiz\" + 10 + 20); \n   }  \n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"1020GeeksQuiz\nGeeksQuiz1020","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"30GeeksQuiz\nGeeksQuiz30","answer_d":"1020GeeksQuiz\nGeeksQuiz30","answer_c":"30GeeksQuiz\nGeeksQuiz1020"},"q37":{"question":"Predict the output of following Java program\n\nclass Main {\n   public static void main(String args[]) {\n      try {\n         throw 10;\n      }\n      catch(int e) {\n         System.out.println(\"Got the  Exception \" + e);\n      }\n  }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Got the Exception 0","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Got the Exception 10","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q36":{"question":"\nclass Test\n{\n    static int a;\n    \n    static\n    {\n        a = 4;\n        System.out.println (\"inside static blockn\");\n        System.out.println (\"a = \" + a);\n    }\n    \n    Test()\n    {\n        System.out.println (\"ninside constructorn\");\n        a = 10;\n    }\n    \n    public static void func()\n    {\n        a = a + 1;\n        System.out.println (\"a = \" + a);\n    }\n    \n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n\n        Test obj = new Test();\n        obj.func();\n\n    }\n}\n ","hint":"None","answer_b":"Compiler Error","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"inside static block\na = 4\ninside constructor\na = 11","answer_d":"inside static block\na = 4\ninside constructor\na = 5","answer_c":"Run Time Error"},"q39":{"question":"Output of following Java program?\n\nclass Main {\n   public static void main(String args[]) {\n      int x = 0;\n      int y = 10;\n      int z = y/x;\n  }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Compiles and runs fine","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Compiler Error","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Compiles fine but throws ArithmeticException exception"},"q38":{"question":"\nclass Test extends Exception { }\n \nclass Main {\n   public static void main(String args[]) { \n      try {\n         throw new Test();\n      }\n      catch(Test t) {\n         System.out.println(\"Got the Test Exception\");\n      }\n      finally {\n         System.out.println(\"Inside finally block \");\n      }\n  }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Got the Test Exception","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Got the Test Exception\nInside finally block ","answer_d":"Compiler Error","answer_c":"Inside finally block "},"q80":{"question":"Which of the following is not an operator in Java?","hint":"None","answer_b":"sizeof","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"instanceof","answer_d":">>>=","answer_c":"new"},"q82":{"question":"\nclass Test\n{\n    public static void main(String args[])\n    {\n        String s1 = \"geeksquiz\";\n        String s2 = \"geeksquiz\";\n        System.out.println(\"s1 == s2 is:\" + s1 == s2);\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"false","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"true","answer_d":"throws an exception","answer_c":"compiler error"},"q81":{"question":"\nclass Base {}\n\nclass Derived extends Base {\n   public static void main(String args[]){\n      Base a = new Derived();\n      System.out.println(a instanceof Derived);\n   }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"false","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"true","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q40":{"question":"\nclass Base extends Exception {}\nclass Derived extends Base  {}\n\npublic class Main {\n  public static void main(String args[]) {\n   // some other stuff\n   try {\n       // Some monitored code\n       throw new Derived();\n    }\n    catch(Base b)     { \n       System.out.println(\"Caught base class exception\"); \n    }\n    catch(Derived d)  { \n       System.out.println(\"Caught derived class exception\"); \n    }\n  }\n} ","hint":"None","answer_b":"Caught derived class exception","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Caught base class exception","answer_d":"Compiler Error because base class exception is caught before derived class","answer_c":"Compiler Error because derived is not throwable"},"q84":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\n class Test\n{\n    boolean[] array = new boolean[3];\n    int count = 0;\n\n    void set(boolean[] arr, int x)\n    {\n        arr[x] = true;\n        count++;\n    }\n\n    void func()\n    {\n        if(array[0] && array[++count - 2] | array [count - 1])\n            count++;\n\n        System.out.println(\"count = \" + count);\n    }\n\n\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        Test object = new Test();\n        object.set(object.array, 0);\n        object.set(object.array, 1);\n        object.func();\n    }\n}\n ","hint":"None","answer_b":"3","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"2","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"4"},"q83":{"question":"\nclass demo\n{\n    int a, b, c;\n    demo(int a, int b, int c)\n    {\n        this.a = a;\n        this.b = b;\n    }\n    \n    demo()\n    {\n        a = b = c = 0;\n    }\n    \n    demo operator+(const demo &obj)\n    {\n        demo object;\n        object.a = this.a + obj.a;\n        object.b = this.b + obj.b;\n        object.c = this.c + obj.c;\n        return object;\n    }\n}\n\nclass Test\n{\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n\n        demo obj1 = new demo(1, 2, 3);\n        demo obj2 = new demo(1, 2, 3);\n        demo obj3 = new demo();\n\n        obj3 = obj1 + obj2;\n        System.out.println (\"obj3.a = \" + obj3.a);\n        System.out.println (\"obj3.b = \" + obj3.c);\n        System.out.println (\"obj3.c = \" + obj3.c);\n\n    }\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"Run Time Error","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Compile Error","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Segmentation Fault"},"q42":{"question":"\nclass Test\n{\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        try\n        {\n            int a[]= {1, 2, 3, 4};\n            for (int i = 1; i <= 4; i++)\n            {\n                System.out.println (\"a[\" + i + \"]=\" + a[i] + \"n\");\n            }\n        }\n        \n        catch (Exception e)\n        {\n            System.out.println (\"error = \" + e);\n        }\n        \n        catch (ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException e)\n        {\n            System.out.println (\"ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException\");\n        }\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Run time error","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Compiler error","answer_d":"Error Code is printed","answer_c":"ArrayIndexOutOfBoundsException"},"q41":{"question":"\nclass Test\n{\n    public static void main (String[] args)\n    {\n        try\n        {\n            int a = 0;\n            System.out.println (\"a = \" + a);\n            int b = 20 / a;\n            System.out.println (\"b = \" + b);\n        }\n\n        catch(ArithmeticException e)\n        {\n            System.out.println (\"Divide by zero error\");\n        }\n\n        finally\n        {\n            System.out.println (\"inside the finally block\");\n        }\n    }\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"Divide by zero error","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Compile error","answer_d":"a = 0","answer_c":"\na = 0\nDivide by zero error\ninside the finally block"},"q85":{"question":"What is the output of the following Java program?\nClass Test\n{\n public static void main (String [] args)\n {\n int x = 0;\n int y = 0;\n for (int z = 0; z < 5; z++)\n {\n if((++x > 2) || (++y > 2))\n {\n x++;\n }\n }\n System.out.println( x + \" \" + y);\n }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"8 5","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"8 2","answer_d":"5 3","answer_c":"8 3"},"q44":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\nclass Test\n{   int count = 0;\n\n    void A() throws Exception\n    {\n        try\n        {\n            count++;\n            \n            try\n            {\n                count++;\n\n                try\n                {\n                    count++;\n                    throw new Exception();\n\n                }\n                \n                catch(Exception ex)\n                {\n                    count++;\n                    throw new Exception();\n                }\n            }\n            \n            catch(Exception ex)\n            {\n                count++;\n            }\n        }\n        \n        catch(Exception ex)\n        {\n            count++;\n        }\n\n    }\n\n    void display()\n    {\n        System.out.println(count);\n    }\n\n    public static void main(String[] args) throws Exception\n    {\n        Test obj = new Test();\n        obj.A();\n        obj.display();\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"5","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"4","answer_d":"Compilation error","answer_c":"6"},"q43":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\nclass Test\n{\n    String str = \"a\";\n\n    void A()\n    {\n        try\n        {\n            str +=\"b\";\n            B();\n        }\n        catch (Exception e)\n        {\n            str += \"c\";\n        }\n    }\n\n    void B() throws Exception\n    {\n        try\n        {\n            str += \"d\";\n            C();\n        }\n        catch(Exception e)\n        {\n            throw new Exception();\n        }\n        finally\n        {\n            str += \"e\";\n        }\n\n        str += \"f\";\n\n    }\n    \n    void C() throws Exception\n    {\n        throw new Exception();\n    }\n\n    void display()\n    {\n        System.out.println(str);\n    }\n\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        Test object = new Test();\n        object.A();\n        object.display();\n    }\n\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"abdec","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"abdef","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"abdefc"},"q46":{"question":"The built-in base class in Java, which is used to handle all exceptions is","hint":"None","answer_b":"Exception","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Raise","answer_d":"Throwable","answer_c":"Error"},"q45":{"question":"Which of these is a super class of all errors and exceptions in the Java language?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Throwable","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"RunTimeExceptions","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"Catchable"},"q48":{"question":"Which of the following is/are advantages of packages?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Classes, even though they are visible outside their package, can have fields visible to packages only","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Packages avoid name clashes","answer_d":"All of the above","answer_c":"We can have hidden classes that are used by the packages, but not visible outside."},"q47":{"question":"Which of the following is/are true about packages in Java?\n\n1) Every class is part of some package. \n2) All classes in a file are part of the same package. \n3) If no package is specified, the classes in the file \n   go into a special unnamed package \n4) If no package is specified, a new package is created with \n   folder name of class and the class is put in this package. ","hint":"None","answer_b":"Only 1, 2 and 4","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Only 1, 2 and 3","answer_d":"Only 1 and 3","answer_c":"Only 4"},"q49":{"question":"Predict the output of following Java program\n\n// Note static keyword after import.\nimport static java.lang.System.*;\n  \nclass StaticImportDemo\n{\n   public static void main(String args[])\n   {      \n        out.println(\"GeeksforGeeks\");\n   }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Runtime Error","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Compiler Error","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"GeeksforGeeks"},"q51":{"question":"Which one of the following is correct?","hint":"None","answer_b":"An applet is not a small program","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Java applets can not be written in any programming language","answer_d":"Applets are embedded in another applications","answer_c":"An applet can be run on its own"},"q50":{"question":"Which of the following statement(s) is/are TRUE regarding Java Servelets ? (a) A Java Servlet is a server-side component that runs on the web server and extends the capabilities of a server. (b) A Servlet can use the user interface classes like AWT or Swing.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Only (b) is TRUE.","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Only (a) is TRUE.","answer_d":"Neither (a) nor (b) is TRUE.","answer_c":"Both (a) and (b) are TRUE."},"q53":{"question":"Predict the output of following Java program\n\nclass Test {\n  int i;\n} \nclass Main {\n  public static void main(String args[]) { \n      Test t = new Test(); \n      System.out.println(t.i);\n   } \n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"0","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"garbage value","answer_d":"runtime error","answer_c":"compiler error"},"q52":{"question":"Predict the output of following Java program?\n\nclass Test {\n  int i;\n} \nclass Main {\n   public static void main(String args[]) { \n     Test t; \n     System.out.println(t.i); \n}  ","hint":"None","answer_b":"garbage value","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"0","answer_d":"runtime error","answer_c":"compiler error"},"q11":{"question":"Which of the following is true about interfaces in java.\n\n\n1) An interface can contain following type of members.\n....public, static, final fields (i.e., constants) \n....default and static methods with bodies\n\n2) An instance of interface can be created.\n\n3) A class can implement multiple interfaces.\n\n4) Many classes can implement the same interface.","hint":"None","answer_b":"1, 2 and 4","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"1, 3 and 4","answer_d":"1, 2, 3 and 4","answer_c":"2, 3 and 4"},"q55":{"question":"Predict the output of following Java program. \n\n class demoClass\n{\n    int a = 1;\n\n    void func()\n    {\n        demo obj = new demo();\n        obj.display();\n    }\n\n\n    class demo\n    {\n        int b = 2;\n\n        void display()\n        {\n            System.out.println(\"na = \" + a);\n        }\n    }\n\n    void get()\n    {\n        System.out.println(\"nb = \" + b);\n    }\n}\n\n\nclass Test\n{\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        demoClass obj = new demoClass();\n        obj.func();\n        obj.get();\n\n    }\n}\n\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"Compilation error","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"a = 1\nb = 2","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"b = 2\na = 1"},"q10":{"question":"Which of the following is FALSE about abstract classes in Java","hint":"None","answer_b":"Abstract classes can have constructors","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"If we derive an abstract class and do not implement all the abstract methods, then the derived class should also be marked as abstract using 'abstract' keyword","answer_d":"A class can inherit from multiple abstract classes.","answer_c":"A class can be made abstract without any abstract method"},"q54":{"question":"\nclass demo\n{\n    int a, b;\n    \n    demo()\n    {\n        a = 10;\n        b = 20;\n    }\n    \n    public void print()\n    {\n        System.out.println (\"a = \" + a + \" b = \" + b + \"n\");\n    }\n}\n\nclass Test\n{\n\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        demo obj1 = new demo();\n        demo obj2 = obj1;\n\n        obj1.a += 1;\n        obj1.b += 1;\n\n        System.out.println (\"values of obj1 : \");\n        obj1.print();\n        System.out.println (\"values of obj2 : \");\n        obj2.print();\n\n    }\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"values of obj1: \na = 11 b = 21\nvalues of obj2: \na = 11 b = 21","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Compile error","answer_d":"values of obj1: \na = 11 b = 20\nvalues of obj2: \na = 10 b = 21","answer_c":"values of obj1: \na = 11 b = 21\nvalues of obj2: \na = 10 b = 20"},"q13":{"question":"Type IV JDBC driver is a driver","hint":"None","answer_b":"which requires an intermediate layer","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"which is written in C++","answer_d":"which translates JDBC function calls into API not native to DBMS","answer_c":"which communicates through Java sockets"},"q57":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\n class Test\n{\n    int a = 1;\n    int b = 2;\n\n    Test func(Test obj)\n    {\n        Test obj3 = new Test();\n        obj3 = obj;\n        obj3.a = obj.a++ + ++obj.b;\n        obj.b = obj.b;\n        return obj3;\n    }\n\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        Test obj1 = new Test();\n        Test obj2 = obj1.func(obj1);\n\n        System.out.println(\"obj1.a = \" + obj1.a + \"  obj1.b = \" + obj1.b);\n        System.out.println(\"obj2.a = \" + obj2.a + \"  obj1.b = \" + obj2.b);\n\n    }\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"obj1.a = 4  obj1.b = 3\nobj2.a = 4  obj2.b = 3","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"obj1.a = 1  obj1.b = 2\nobj2.a = 4  obj2.b = 3","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Compilation error"},"q12":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\nabstract class demo\n{\n    public int a;\n    demo()\n    {\n        a = 10;\n    }\n\n    abstract public void set();\n    \n    abstract final public void get();\n\n}\n\nclass Test extends demo\n{\n\n    public void set(int a)\n    {\n        this.a = a;\n    }\n\n    final public void get()\n    {\n        System.out.println(\"a = \" + a);\n    }\n\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        Test obj = new Test();\n        obj.set(20);\n        obj.get();\n    }\n}\n ","hint":"None","answer_b":"a = 20","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"a = 10","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Compilation error"},"q56":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\n \nclass First\n{\n\n    void display()\n    {\n        System.out.println(\"Inside First\");\n    }\n}\n\nclass Second extends First\n{\n\n    void display()\n    {\n        System.out.println(\"Inside Second\");\n    }\n}\n\n\nclass Test\n{\n\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        First obj1 =  new First();\n        Second obj2 =  new Second();\n\n        First ref;\n        ref = obj1;\n        ref.display();\n\n        ref = obj2;\n        ref.display();\n    }\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"Inside First\nInside Second","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Compilation error","answer_d":"Runtime error","answer_c":"Inside First\nInside First"},"q15":{"question":"Which of the following is used to make an Abstract class?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Making atleast one member function as virtual function","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Making atleast one member function as pure virtual function","answer_d":"Declaring as Abstract class using static keyword","answer_c":"Declaring as Abstract class using virtual keyword"},"q59":{"question":"What is the output of the following JAVA program ?\n\nClass Test {\n    public static void main(String[] args) {\n        Test obj = new Test();\n        obj.start();\n    }\n    void start() {\n        String stra = \u201ddo\u201d;\n            String strb = method(stra);\n        System.out.print(\u201c: \u201d+stra + strb);\n    }\n    String method(String stra) {\n        stra = stra + \u201dgood\u201d;\n        System.out.print(stra);\n        return\u201c good\u201d;\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"dogood : gooddogood","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"dogood : dogoodgood","answer_d":"dogood : dogood","answer_c":"dogood : dodogood"},"q14":{"question":"Which of the following statement(s) with regard to an abstract class in JAVA is/are TRUE ? I. An abstract class is one that is not used to create objects. II. An abstract class is designed only to act as a base class to be inherited by other classes.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Only II","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Only I","answer_d":"Both I and II","answer_c":"Neither I nor II"},"q58":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\n class Test\n{\n    int a = 1;\n    int b = 2;\n\n    Test func(Test obj)\n    {\n        Test obj3 = new Test();\n        obj3 = obj;\n        obj3.a = obj.a++ + ++obj.b;\n        obj.b = obj.b;\n        return obj3;\n    }\n\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        Test obj1 = new Test();\n        Test obj2 = obj1.func(obj1);\n\n        System.out.println(\"obj1.a = \" + obj1.a + \"  obj1.b = \" + obj1.b);\n        System.out.println(\"obj2.a = \" + obj2.a + \"  obj1.b = \" + obj2.b);\n\n    }\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"obj1.a = 4  obj1.b = 3\nobj2.a = 4  obj2.b = 3","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"obj1.a = 1  obj1.b = 2\nobj2.a = 4  obj2.b = 3","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Compilation error"},"q17":{"question":"Which of the following is FALSE about arrays on Java","hint":"None","answer_b":"Length of array can be changed after creation of array","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A java array is always an object","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Arrays in Java are always allocated on heap"},"q16":{"question":"We can make a class abstract by","hint":"None","answer_b":"Making at least one member function as virtual function","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Declaring it abstract using the virtual keyword","answer_d":"Making all member function const","answer_c":"Making at least one member function as pure virtual function"},"q19":{"question":"\nclass Test {\n   public static void main(String args[]) {\n     int arr[2];  \n     System.out.println(arr[0]);\n     System.out.println(arr[1]);\n   }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"garbage value\ngarbage value","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"0\n0","answer_d":"Exception","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q18":{"question":"Predict the output?\n\n// file name: Main.java\npublic class Main {\n    public static void main(String args[]) {\n       int arr[] = {10, 20, 30, 40, 50};\n       for(int i=0; i < arr.length; i++)\n       {\n             System.out.print(\" \" + arr[i]);              \n       }\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Compiler Error","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"10 20 30 40 50","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"10 20 30 40"},"q1":{"question":"Output of following Java Program?\n\nclass Base {\n    public void show() {\n       System.out.println(\"Base::show() called\");\n    }\n}\n \nclass Derived extends Base {\n    public void show() {\n       System.out.println(\"Derived::show() called\");\n    }\n}\n \npublic class Main {\n    public static void main(String[] args) {\n        Base b = new Derived();;\n        b.show();\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Base::show() called","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Derived::show() called","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q2":{"question":"\nclass Base {\n    final public void show() {\n       System.out.println(\"Base::show() called\");\n    }\n}\n \nclass Derived extends Base {\n    public void show() {\n       System.out.println(\"Derived::show() called\");\n    }\n}\n \nclass Main {\n    public static void main(String[] args) {\n        Base b = new Derived();;\n        b.show();\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Derived::show() called","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Base::show() called","answer_d":"Runtime Error","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q3":{"question":"\nclass Base {\n    public static void show() {\n       System.out.println(\"Base::show() called\");\n    }\n}\n \nclass Derived extends Base {\n    public static void show() {\n       System.out.println(\"Derived::show() called\");\n    }\n}\n \nclass Main {\n    public static void main(String[] args) {\n        Base b = new Derived();;\n        b.show();\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Derived::show() called","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Base::show() called","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q4":{"question":"Which of the following is true about inheritance in Java?\n\n\n1) Private methods are final.\n2) Protected members are accessible within a package and \n   inherited classes outside the package.\n3) Protected methods are final.\n4) We cannot override private methods. ","hint":"None","answer_b":"Only 1 and 2","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"1, 2 and 4","answer_d":"2, 3 and 4","answer_c":"1, 2 and 3"},"q5":{"question":"Output of following Java program?\n\nclass Base {\n    public void Print() {\n        System.out.println(\"Base\");\n    }         \n}\n\nclass Derived extends Base {    \n    public void Print() {\n        System.out.println(\"Derived\");\n    }\n}\n\nclass Main{\n    public static void DoPrint( Base o ) {\n        o.Print();   \n    }\n    public static void main(String[] args) {\n        Base x = new Base();\n        Base y = new Derived();\n        Derived z = new Derived();\n        DoPrint(x);\n        DoPrint(y);\n        DoPrint(z);\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Base\nBase\nDerived","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Base\nDerived\nDerived","answer_d":"Compiler Error","answer_c":"Base\nDerived\nBase"},"q6":{"question":"Predict the output of following program. Note that fun() is public in base and private in derived.\n\nclass Base {\n    public void foo() { System.out.println(\"Base\"); }\n}\n \nclass Derived extends Base {\n    private void foo() { System.out.println(\"Derived\"); } \n}\n \npublic class Main {\n    public static void main(String args[]) {\n        Base b = new Derived();\n        b.foo();\n    }\n} ","hint":"None","answer_b":"Derived","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Base","answer_d":"Runtime Error","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q7":{"question":"Which of the following is true about inheritance in Java. 1) In Java all classes inherit from the Object class directly or indirectly. The Object class is root of all classes. 2) Multiple inheritance is not allowed in Java. 3) Unlike C++, there is nothing like type of inheritance in Java where we can specify whether the inheritance is protected, public or private.","hint":"None","answer_b":"1 and 2","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"1, 2 and 3","answer_d":"1 and 3","answer_c":"2 and 3"},"q8":{"question":"Predict the output of following Java Program\n\n// filename Main.java\nclass Grandparent {\n    public void Print() {\n        System.out.println(\"Grandparent's Print()\");\n    }\n}\n \nclass Parent extends Grandparent {\n    public void Print() {\n        System.out.println(\"Parent's Print()\");\n    }\n}\n \nclass Child extends Parent {\n    public void Print() {\n        super.super.Print(); \n        System.out.println(\"Child's Print()\");\n    }\n}\n \npublic class Main {\n    public static void main(String[] args) {\n        Child c = new Child();\n        c.Print();\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Grandparent's Print()\nParent's Print()\nChild's Print()","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Compiler Error in super.super.Print()","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Runtime Error"},"q9":{"question":"\nfinal class Complex {\n\n    private final double re;\n    private final double im;\n\n    public Complex(double re, double im) {\n        this.re = re;\n        this.im = im;\n    }\n\n    public String toString() {\n        return \"(\" + re + \" + \" + im + \"i)\";\n    }\n}\n\nclass Main {\n  public static void main(String args[])\n  {\n       Complex c = new Complex(10, 15);\n       System.out.println(\"Complex number is \" + c);\n  }         \n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Compiler Error","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Complex number is (10.0 + 15.0i)","answer_d":"Complex number is Complex@8e2fb5\nHere 8e2fb5 is hash code of c","answer_c":"Complex number is SOME_GARBAGE"},"q60":{"question":"Java uses threads to enable the entire environment to be ______.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Asymmetric","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Symmetric","answer_d":"Asynchronous","answer_c":"Synchronous"},"q62":{"question":"Output of following Java program?\n\nclass Main {\n    public static void main(String args[]) {   \n             System.out.println(fun());\n    } \n \n    int fun()\n    {\n      return 20;\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"compiler error","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"20","answer_d":"garbage balue","answer_c":"0"},"q61":{"question":"In Java, when we implement an interface method, it must be declared as:","hint":"None","answer_b":"Protected","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Private","answer_d":"Friend","answer_c":"Public"},"q20":{"question":"\nclass Test {\n   public static void main(String args[]) {\n     int arr[] = new int[2];  \n     System.out.println(arr[0]);\n     System.out.println(arr[1]);\n   }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"garbage value\ngarbage value","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"0\n0","answer_d":"Exception","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q64":{"question":"\nclass Test {\npublic static void swap(Integer i, Integer j) {\n      Integer temp = new Integer(i);\n      i = j;\n      j = temp;\n   }\n   public static void main(String[] args) {\n      Integer i = new Integer(10);\n      Integer j = new Integer(20);\n      swap(i, j);\n      System.out.println(\"i = \" + i + \", j = \" + j);\n   }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"i = 20, j = 10","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"i = 10, j = 20","answer_d":"i = 20, j = 20","answer_c":"i = 10, j = 10"},"q63":{"question":"\npublic class Main { \n    public static void main(String args[]) { \n       String x = null; \n       giveMeAString(x); \n       System.out.println(x); \n    } \n    static void giveMeAString(String y) \n    { \n       y = \"GeeksQuiz\"; \n    } \n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"null","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"GeeksQuiz","answer_d":"Exception","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q22":{"question":"Output of following Java program?\n\nclass Test\n{\n    public static void main (String[] args) \n    {\n        int arr1[] = {1, 2, 3};\n        int arr2[] = {1, 2, 3};\n        if (arr1 == arr2) \n            System.out.println(\"Same\");\n        else\n            System.out.println(\"Not same\");\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Not Same","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Same","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q66":{"question":"In Java, can we make functions inline like C++?","hint":"None","answer_b":"No","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Yes","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q21":{"question":"\npublic class Main {\n    public static void main(String args[]) {\n        int arr[][] = new int[4][];\n        arr[0] = new int[1];\n        arr[1] = new int[2];\n        arr[2] = new int[3];\n        arr[3] = new int[4];\n \n        int i, j, k = 0;\n        for (i = 0; i < 4; i++) {\n            for (j = 0; j < i + 1; j++) {\n                arr[i][j] = k;\n                k++;\n            }\n        }\n        for (i = 0; i < 4; i++) {\n            for (j = 0; j < i + 1; j++) {\n                System.out.print(\" \" + arr[i][j]);\n                k++;\n            }\n            System.out.println();\n        }\n    }\n} ","hint":"None","answer_b":"\n 0\n 1 2\n 3 4 5\n 6 7 8 9 ","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Compiler Error","answer_d":"\n 9\n 7 8\n 4 5 6\n 0 1 2 3 ","answer_c":"\n 0\n 0 0\n 0 0 0\n 0 0 0 0 "},"q65":{"question":"\nclass intWrap {\n   int x;\n} \npublic class Main { \n    public static void main(String[] args) {\n       intWrap i = new intWrap();\n       i.x = 10;\n       intWrap j = new intWrap();\n       j.x = 20;\n       swap(i, j);\n       System.out.println(\"i.x = \" + i.x + \", j.x = \" + j.x);\n    } \n    public static void swap(intWrap i, intWrap j) {\n       int temp = i.x;\n       i.x = j.x;\n       j.x = temp;\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"i.x = 10, j.x = 20","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"i.x = 20, j.x = 10","answer_d":"i.x = 20, j.x = 20","answer_c":"i.x = 10, j.x = 10"},"q24":{"question":"\nclass Test\n{\n    public static void main (String[] args) \n    {\n        int arr1[] = {1, 2, 3};\n        int arr2[] = {1, 2, 3};\n        if (arr1.equals(arr2))\n            System.out.println(\"Same\");\n        else\n            System.out.println(\"Not same\");\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Not same","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Same","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q68":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\nclass Test\n{\n    public void demo(String str)\n    {\n        String[] arr = str.split(\";\");\n        for (String s : arr)\n        {\n            System.out.println(s);\n        }\n    }\n\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        char array[] = {'a', 'b', ' ', 'c', 'd', ';', 'e', 'f', ' ', \n                        'g', 'h', ';', 'i', 'j', ' ', 'k', 'l'};\n        String str = new String(array);\n        Test obj = new Test();\n        obj.demo(str);\n    }\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"ab\ncd;ef\ngh;ij\nkl","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"ab cd\nef gh\nij kl","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"Compilation error"},"q23":{"question":"Output of following Java program?\n\nimport java.util.Arrays;\nclass Test\n{\n    public static void main (String[] args) \n    {\n        int arr1[] = {1, 2, 3};\n        int arr2[] = {1, 2, 3};\n        if (Arrays.equals(arr1, arr2))\n            System.out.println(\"Same\");\n        else\n            System.out.println(\"Not same\");\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Not Same","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Same","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q67":{"question":"Predict the output?\n\nclass Main {\n    public static void main(String args[]) {   \n             System.out.println(fun());\n    }   \n    static int fun(int x = 0)\n    {\n      return x;\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Garbage Value","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"0","answer_d":"Runtime Error","answer_c":"Compiler Error"},"q26":{"question":"\nclass Main {   \n   public static void main(String args[]) {      \n         int t;      \n         System.out.println(t); \n    }   \n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"garbage value","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"0","answer_d":"runtime error","answer_c":"compiler error"},"q25":{"question":"Consider the following C program which is supposed to compute the transpose of a given 4 x 4 matrix M. Note that, there is an X in the program which indicates some missing statements. Choose the correct option to replace X in the program.\n\n#include<stdio.h>\n#define ROW 4\n#define COL 4\nint M[ROW][COL] = {1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16};\nmain()\n{\n    int i, j, t;\n    for (i = 0; i < 4; ++i)\n    {\n        X\n    }\n    for (1 = 0; i < 4; ++i)\n        for (j = 0; j < 4; ++j)\n            printf (\"%d\", M[i][j]);\n}\n \nA)\t\nfor(j = 0; j < 4; ++j){\n     t = M[i][j];\n     M[i][j] = M[j][i];\n     M[j][i] = t;\n}\n \nB)\t\nfor(j = 0; j < 4; ++j){\n     M[i][j] = t;\n     t = M[j][i];\n     M[j][i] = M[i][j];\n}\n \nC)\n\t\nfor(j = i; j < 4; ++j){\n     t = M[i][j];\n     M[i][j] = M[j][i];\n     M[j][i] = t;\n}\n \nD)\t\nfor(j = i; j < 4; ++j){\n     M[i][j] = t;\n     t = M[j][i];\n     M[j][i] = M[i][j];\n}\n ","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q69":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\n\nclass Test\n{\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        StringBuffer a = new StringBuffer(\"geeks\");\n        StringBuffer b = new StringBuffer(\"forgeeks\");\n        a.delete(1,3);\n        a.append(b);\n        System.out.println(a);\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"gksforgeeks","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"gsforgeeks","answer_d":"Compilation error","answer_c":"geksforgeeks"},"q28":{"question":"Predict the output of the following program.\n\n class Test\n{\n    public static void main(String[] args)\n    {\n        Double object = new Double(\"2.4\");\n        int a = object.intValue();\n        byte b = object.byteValue();\n        float d = object.floatValue();\n        double c = object.doubleValue();\n\n        System.out.println(a + b + c + d );\n\n    }\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"8.8","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"8","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"8.800000095367432"},"q27":{"question":"Predict the output of following Java program.\n\nclass Test { \n    public static void main(String[] args) { \n      for(int i = 0; 0; i++) \n      { \n          System.out.println(\"Hello\"); \n          break; \n      } \n    } \n} ","hint":"None","answer_b":"Empty Output","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Hello","answer_d":"Runtime error","answer_c":"Compiler error"},"q29":{"question":"Which of the following statements is/are TRUE regarding JAVA ? (a) Constants that cannot be changed are declared using the \u2018static\u2019 keyword. (b) A class can only inherit one class but can implement multiple interfaces.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Only (b) is TRUE.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Only (a) is TRUE.","answer_d":"Neither (a) nor (b) are TRUE.","answer_c":"Both (a) and (b) are TRUE."}},"Algorithms":{"q71":{"question":"Consider the following graph, \n \n Among the following sequences:\n(I) a b e g h f \n(II) a b f e h g\n(III) a b f h g e \n(IV) a f g h b e  \nWhich are depth first traversals of the above graph?","hint":"None","answer_b":"I and IV only","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"I, II and IV only","answer_d":"I, III and IV only","answer_c":"II, III and IV only"},"q70":{"question":"Let G be an undirected graph. Consider a depth-first traversal of G, and let T be the resulting depth-first search tree. Let u be a vertex in G and let v be the first new (unvisited) vertex visited after visiting u in the traversal. Which of the following statements is always true? (GATE CS 2000)","hint":"None","answer_b":"{u,v} must be an edge in G, and v is a descendant of u in T","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"{u,v} must be an edge in G, and u is a descendant of v in T","answer_d":"If {u,v} is not an edge in G then u and v must have the same parent in T","answer_c":"If {u,v} is not an edge in G then u is a leaf in T"},"q73":{"question":"Given two vertices in a graph s and t, which of the two traversals (BFS and DFS) can be used to find if there is path from s to t?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Only DFS","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Only BFS","answer_d":"Neither BFS nor DFS","answer_c":"Both BFS and DFS"},"q72":{"question":"Make is a utility that automatically builds executable programs and libraries from source code by reading files called makefiles which specify how to derive the target program. Which of the following standard graph algorithms is used by Make.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Topological Sorting","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Strongly Connected Components","answer_d":"Dijkstra's Shortest Path","answer_c":"Breadth First Search"},"q75":{"question":"Is following statement true/false If a DFS of a directed graph contains a back edge, any other DFS of the same graph will also contain at least one back edge. Source: http://courses.csail.mit.edu/6.006/oldquizzes/solutions/q2-s2009-sol.pdf","hint":"None","answer_b":"False","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"True","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q74":{"question":"Which of the following condition is sufficient to detect cycle in a directed graph?","hint":"None","answer_b":"There is an edge from currently being visited node to an ancestor of currently visited node in DFS forest.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"There is an edge from currently being visited node to an already visited node.","answer_d":"None of the bove","answer_c":"Every node is seen twice in DFS."},"q77":{"question":"Consider the directed graph shown in the figure below. There are multiple shortest paths between vertices S and T. Which one will be reported by Dijstra?s shortest path algorithm? Assume that, in any iteration, the shortest path to a vertex v is updated only when a strictly shorter path to v is discovered.","hint":"None","answer_b":"SBDT","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"SDT","answer_d":"SACET","answer_c":"SACDT"},"q76":{"question":"Which of the following is not a backtracking algorithm?","hint":"None","answer_b":"N queen problem","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Knight tour problem","answer_d":"M coloring problem","answer_c":"Tower of hanoi"},"q79":{"question":"Dijkstra\u2019s single source shortest path algorithm when run from vertex a in the below graph, computes the correct shortest path distance to","hint":"None","answer_b":"only vertices a, e, f, g, h","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"only vertex a","answer_d":"all the vertices","answer_c":"only vertices a, b, c, d"},"q78":{"question":"To implement Dijkstra\u2019s shortest path algorithm on unweighted graphs so that it runs in linear time, the data structure to be used is:","hint":"None","answer_b":"Stack","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Queue","answer_d":"B-Tree","answer_c":"Heap"},"q80":{"question":"In an unweighted, undirected connected graph, the shortest path from a node S to every other node is computed most efficiently, in terms of time complexity by","hint":"None","answer_b":"Warshall\u2019s algorithm","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Dijkstra\u2019s algorithm starting from S.","answer_d":"Performing a BFS starting from S.","answer_c":"Performing a DFS starting from S."},"q82":{"question":"What is the time complexity of Bellman-Ford single-source shortest path algorithm on a complete graph of n vertices?","hint":"None","answer_b":"[Tex]\\Theta(n^2 Logn)[/Tex]","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"[Tex]\\Theta(n^2)[/Tex]","answer_d":"[Tex]\\Theta(n^3 Logn)[/Tex]","answer_c":"[Tex]\\Theta(n^3)[/Tex]"},"q81":{"question":"Suppose we run Dijkstra\u2019s single source shortest-path algorithm on the following edge weighted directed graph with vertex P as the source. In what order do the nodes get included into the set of vertices for which the shortest path distances are finalized? (GATE CS 2004)","hint":"None","answer_b":"P, Q, R, U, S, T","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"P, Q, R, S, T, U","answer_d":"P, Q, T, R, U, S","answer_c":"P, Q, R, U, T, S"},"q84":{"question":"Following statement is true or false?\n\nIf we make following changes to  Dijkstra, then it can be used to find \nthe longest simple path, assume that the graph is acyclic.\n\n1) Initialize all distances as minus infinite instead of plus infinite.\n\n2) Modify the relax condition in  Dijkstra's algorithm to update distance\n  of an adjacent v of the currently considered vertex u only\n  if \"dist[u]+graph[u][v] > dist[v]\". In shortest path algo, \n  the sign is opposite. ","hint":"None","answer_b":"False","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"True","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q83":{"question":"In a weighted graph, assume that the shortest path from a source 's' to a destination 't' is correctly calculated using a shortest path algorithm. Is the following statement true? If we increase weight of every edge by 1, the shortest path always remains same.","hint":"None","answer_b":"No","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Yes","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q86":{"question":"Given a directed graph where weight of every edge is same, we can efficiently find shortest path from a given source to destination using?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Dijkstra's Shortest Path Algorithm","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Breadth First Traversal","answer_d":"Depth First Search","answer_c":"Neither Breadth First Traversal nor Dijkstra's algorithm can be used"},"q85":{"question":"Which of the following algorithm can be used to efficiently calculate single source shortest paths in a Directed Acyclic Graph?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Bellman-Ford","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Dijkstra","answer_d":"Strongly Connected Component","answer_c":"Topological Sort"},"q88":{"question":"The length of the path from v5 to v6 in the MST of previous question with n = 10 is","hint":"None","answer_b":"25","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"11","answer_d":"41","answer_c":"31"},"q115":{"question":"Suppose you are given an array s[1...n] and a procedure reverse (s,i,j) which reverses the order of elements in a between positions i and j (both inclusive). What does the following sequence\ndo, where 1 < k <= n:\n  reverse (s, 1, k);\n  reverse (s, k + 1, n);\n  reverse (s, 1, n);\n(GATE CS 2000)","hint":"None","answer_b":"Leaves s unchanged","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Rotates s left by k positions","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"Reverses all elements of s"},"q87":{"question":"An undirected graph G(V, E) contains n ( n > 2 ) nodes named v1 , v2 ,\u2026.vn. Two nodes vi , vj are connected if and only if 0 < |i \u2013 j| <= 2. Each edge (vi, vj ) is assigned a weight i + j. A sample graph with n = 4 is shown below. What will be the cost of the minimum spanning tree (MST) of such a graph with n nodes? (GATE CS 2011)","hint":"None","answer_b":"n^2 \u2013 n + 1","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"1/12(11n^2 \u2013 5n)","answer_d":"2n + 1","answer_c":"6n \u2013 11"},"q116":{"question":"An inversion in a an array A[] is a pair (A[i], A[j]) such that A[i] > A[j] and i < j. An array will have maximum number of inversions if it is:","hint":"None","answer_b":"Sorted in decreasing order","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Sorted in increasing order","answer_d":"Both A and B","answer_c":"Sorted in alternate fashion"},"q89":{"question":"Consider a complete undirected graph with vertex set {0, 1, 2, 3, 4}. Entry Wij in the matrix W below is the weight of the edge {i, j}. What is the minimum possible weight of a spanning tree T in this graph such that vertex 0 is a leaf node in the tree T? (GATE CS 2010)","hint":"None","answer_b":"8","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"7","answer_d":"10","answer_c":"9"},"q111":{"question":"A set X can be represented by an array x[n] as follows: \n Consider the following algorithm in which x,y and z are Boolean arrays of size n:\n\nalgorithm zzz(x[] , y[], z [])\n{\n   int i;\n   for (i=O; i<n; ++i)\n     z[i] = (x[i] ^ ~y[i]) V (~x[i] ^ y[i])\n}\nThe set Z computed by the algorithm is:","hint":"None","answer_b":"(X Union Y)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"(X Intersection Y)","answer_d":"(X-Y) Union (Y-X)","answer_c":"(X-Y) Intersection (Y-X)"},"q112":{"question":"The minimum number of comparisons required to determine if an integer appears more than n/2 times in a sorted array of n integers is (A) (n) (B) (logn) (C) (log*n) (D) (n)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q113":{"question":"An element in an array X is called a leader if it is greater than all elements to the right of it in X. The best algorithm to find all leaders in an array (GATE CS 2006)","hint":"None","answer_b":"Solves it in linear time using a right to left pass of the array","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Solves it in linear time using a left to right pass of the array","answer_d":"Solves it in time 8(n2)","answer_c":"Solves it using divide and conquer in time 8(nlogn)"},"q114":{"question":"Consider the following C function.\n\nfloat f(float x, int y) \n{ \n  float p, s; int i; \n  for (s=1, p=1, i=1; i < y; i ++) \n  { \n    p*= x/i; \n    s+=p; \n  } \n  return s; \n}   \nFor large values of y, the return value of the function f best approximates (GATE CS 2003)","hint":"None","answer_b":"e^x","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"x^y","answer_d":"x^x","answer_c":"ln(1 + x)"},"q91":{"question":"An undirected graph G has n nodes. Its adjacency matrix is given by an n × n square matrix whose (i) diagonal elements are 0\u2018s and (ii) non-diagonal elements are 1\u2018s. which one of the following is TRUE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Graph G has a unique MST of cost n-1","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Graph G has no minimum spanning tree (MST)","answer_d":"Graph G has multiple spanning trees of different costs","answer_c":"Graph G has multiple distinct MSTs, each of cost n-1"},"q90":{"question":"In the graph given in above question question, what is the minimum possible weight of a path P from vertex 1 to vertex 2 in this graph such that P contains at most 3 edges?","hint":"None","answer_b":"8","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"7","answer_d":"10","answer_c":"9"},"q93":{"question":"Let G be an undirected connected graph with distinct edge weight. Let emax be the edge with maximum weight and emin the edge with minimum weight. Which of the following statements is false? (GATE CS 2000)","hint":"None","answer_b":"If emax is in a minimum spanning tree, then its removal must disconnect G","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Every minimum spanning tree of G must contain emin","answer_d":"G has a unique minimum spanning tree","answer_c":"No minimum spanning tree contains emax"},"q92":{"question":"Consider the following graph: Which one of the following cannot be the sequence of edges added, in that order, to a minimum spanning tree using Kruskal\u2019s algorithm?","hint":"None","answer_b":"(a\u2014b),(d\u2014f),(d\u2014c),(b\u2014f),(d\u2014e)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"(a\u2014b),(d\u2014f),(b\u2014f),(d\u2014c),(d\u2014e)","answer_d":"(d\u2014f),(a\u2014b),(b\u2014f),(d\u2014e),(d\u2014c)","answer_c":"(d\u2014f),(a\u2014b),(d\u2014c),(b\u2014f),(d\u2014e)"},"q95":{"question":"Let G be a weighted graph with edge weights greater than one and G'be the graph constructed by squaring the weights of edges in G. Let T and T' be the minimum spanning trees of G and G', respectively, with total weights t and t'. Which of the following statements is TRUE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"T' = T with total weight t' < t2","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"T' = T with total weight t' = t2","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"T' != T but total weight t' = t2"},"q94":{"question":"Consider a weighted complete graph G on the vertex set {v1,v2 ,v} such that the weight of the edge (v,,v) is 2|i-j|. The weight of a minimum spanning tree of G is: (GATE CS 2006)","hint":"None","answer_b":"2n \u2014 2","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"n \u2014 1","answer_d":"2","answer_c":"nC2"},"q97":{"question":"Assuming P != NP, which of the following is true ? \n(A) NP-complete = NP\n \n(B) NP-complete P = \n \n(C) NP-hard = NP\n \n(D) P = NP-complete","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q96":{"question":"Consider the following graph: \n \n Which one of the following is NOT the sequence of edges added to the minimum spanning tree using Kruskal's algorithm?","hint":"None","answer_b":"(b,e)(e,f)(a,c)(f,g)(b,c)(c,d)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"(b,e)(e,f)(a,c)(b,c)(f,g)(c,d)","answer_d":"(b,e)(e,f)(b,c)(a,c)(f,g)(c,d)","answer_c":"(b,e)(a,c)(e,f)(b,c)(f,g)(c,d)"},"q11":{"question":"What is the output of following program?\n\n#include <stdio.h>\n\nvoid print(int n, int j)\n{\n   if (j >= n)\n      return;\n   if (n-j > 0 && n-j >= j)\n       printf(\"%d %dn\", j, n-j);\n   print(n, j+1);\n}\n\nint main()\n{\n    int n = 8;\n    print(n, 1);\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"1 7\n 2 6\n 3 5\n 4 4","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"1 7\n 2 6\n 3 5\n 4 4\n 4 4","answer_d":"1 2\n 3 4\n 5 6\n 7 8","answer_c":"1 7\n 2 6\n 3 5"},"q99":{"question":"Let X be a problem that belongs to the class NP. Then which one of the following is TRUE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"If X can be solved deterministically in polynomial time, then P = NP.","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"There is no polynomial time algorithm for X.","answer_d":"X may be undecidable.","answer_c":"If X is NP-hard, then it is NP-complete."},"q10":{"question":"Which of the given options provides the increasing order of asymptotic complexity of functions f1, f2, f3 and f4?\n\n  f1(n) = 2^n\n  f2(n) = n^(3/2)\n  f3(n) = nLogn\n  f4(n) = n^(Logn)","hint":"None","answer_b":"f3, f2, f1, f4","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"f3, f2, f4, f1","answer_d":"f2, f3, f4, f1","answer_c":"f2, f3, f1, f4"},"q98":{"question":"Let S be an NP-complete problem and Q and R be two other problems not known to be in NP. Q is polynomial time reducible to S and S is polynomial-time reducible to R. Which one of the following statements is true? (GATE CS 2006)","hint":"None","answer_b":"R is NP-hard","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"R is NP-complete","answer_d":"Q is NP-hard","answer_c":"Q is NP-complete"},"q13":{"question":"Given a sorted array of integers, what can be the minimum worst case time complexity to find ceiling of a number x in given array? Ceiling of an element x is the smallest element present in array which is greater than or equal to x. Ceiling is not present if x is greater than the maximum element present in array. For example, if the given array is {12, 67, 90, 100, 300, 399} and x = 95, then output should be 100.","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(n)","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(LogLogn)","answer_d":"O(Logn * Logn)","answer_c":"O(Logn)"},"q12":{"question":"Which of the following is correct recurrence for worst case of Binary Search?","hint":"None","answer_b":"T(n) = T(n-1) + O(1) and T(1) = T(0) = O(1)","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"T(n) = 2T(n/2) + O(1) and T(1) = T(0) = O(1)","answer_d":"T(n) = T(n-2) + O(1) and T(1) = T(0) = O(1)","answer_c":"T(n) = T(n/2) + O(1) and T(1) = T(0) = O(1)"},"q15":{"question":"In the above question, the correction needed in the program to make it work properly is (GATE CS 2008)","hint":"None","answer_b":"Change line 6 to: if (Y[k] < x) i = k - 1; else j = k+1;","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Change line 6 to: if (Y[k] < x) i = k + 1; else j = k-1;","answer_d":"Change line 7 to: } while ((Y[k] == x) && (i < j));","answer_c":"Change line 6 to: if (Y[k] <= x) i = k; else j = k;"},"q14":{"question":"Consider the following C program that attempts to locate an element x in an array Y[] using binary search. The program is erroneous. (GATE CS 2008)\n\n1.   f(int Y[10], int x) {\n2.     int i, j, k;\n3.     i = 0; j = 9;\n4.     do {\n5.             k =  (i + j) /2;\n6.             if( Y[k] < x)  i = k; else j = k;\n7.         } while(Y[k] != x && i < j);\n8.     if(Y[k] == x) printf (\"x is in the array \") ;\n9.     else printf (\" x is not in the array \") ;\n10. }\nOn which of the following contents of Y and x does the program fail?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Y is [1 3 5 7 9 11 13 15 17 19] and x < 1","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Y is [1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10] and x < 10","answer_d":"Y is [2 4 6 8 10 12 14 16 18 20] and 2 < x < 20 and x is even","answer_c":"Y is [2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2] and x > 2"},"q17":{"question":"Consider the C function given below. Assume that the array listA contains n (> 0) elements, sorted in ascending order.\n\nint ProcessArray(int *listA, int x, int n)\n{\n    int i, j, k;\n    i = 0;\n    j = n-1;\n    do\n    {\n        k = (i+j)/2;\n        if (x <= listA[k])\n            j = k-1;\n        if (listA[k] <= x)\n            i = k+1;\n    }\n    while (i <= j);\n    if (listA[k] == x)\n        return(k);\n    else\n        return -1;\n}\nWhich one of the following statements about the function ProcessArray is CORRECT?","hint":"None","answer_b":"It is an implementation of binary search.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"It will run into an infinite loop when x is not in listA.","answer_d":"It will return −1 even when x is present in listA.","answer_c":"It will always find the maximum element in listA."},"q16":{"question":"You are given a list of 5 integers and these integers are in the range from 1 to 6. There are no duplicates in list. One of the integers is missing in the list. Which of the following expression would give the missing number. ^ is bitwise XOR operator. ~ is bitwise NOT operator. Let elements of list can be accessed as list[0], list[1], list[2], list[3], list[4]","hint":"None","answer_b":"list[0] ^ list[1] ^ list[2] ^ list[3] ^ list[4] ^ 1 ^ 2 ^ 3 ^ 4 ^ 5 ^ 6","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"list[0] ^ list[1] ^ list[2] ^ list[3] ^ list[4]","answer_d":"~(list[0] ^ list[1] ^ list[2] ^ list[3] ^ list[4])","answer_c":"list[0] ^ list[1] ^ list[2] ^ list[3] ^ list[4] ^ 1 ^ 2 ^ 3 ^ 4 ^ 5"},"q19":{"question":"The average number of key comparisons done in a successful sequential search in a list of length it is","hint":"None","answer_b":"(n-1)/2","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"log n","answer_d":"(n+1)/2","answer_c":"n/2"},"q18":{"question":"Consider a sorted array of n numbers. What would be the time complexity of the best known algorithm to find a pair a and b such that |a-b| = k , k being a positive integer.","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(nlog n)","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(n)","answer_d":"O(logn)","answer_c":"O(n2)"},"q20":{"question":"Consider the following program that attempts to locate an element x in a sorted array a[ ] using binary search. Assume N>1. The program is erroneous. Under what conditions does the program fail?\nvar i,j,k: integer;  x: integer;\n    a: array; [1....N] of integer;\nbegin\ti:= 1; j:= N;\nrepeat\t\n    k:(i+j) div 2;\n    if a[k] < x then i:= k \n    else j:= k \nuntil (a[k] = x) or (i >= j);\n    \nif (a[k] = x) then\n    writeln ('x is in the array')\nelse\n    writeln ('x is not in the array')\nend;","hint":"None","answer_b":"x is greater than all elements of the array a[]","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"x is the last element of the array a[]","answer_d":"x is less than the last element of the array a[]","answer_c":"Both of the Above"},"q22":{"question":"Suppose we have a O(n) time algorithm that finds median of an unsorted array. Now consider a QuickSort implementation where we first find median using the above algorithm, then use median as pivot. What will be the worst case time complexity of this modified QuickSort.","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(n^2)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(n^2 Logn)","answer_d":"O(nLogn)","answer_c":"O(n Logn Logn)"},"q21":{"question":"What is recurrence for worst case of QuickSort and what is the time complexity in Worst case?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Recurrence is T(n) = T(n-1) + O(n) and time complexity is O(n^2)","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Recurrence is T(n) = T(n-2) + O(n) and time complexity is O(n^2)","answer_d":"Recurrence is T(n) = T(n/10) + T(9n/10) + O(n) and time complexity is O(nLogn)","answer_c":"Recurrence is T(n) = 2T(n/2) + O(n) and time complexity is O(nLogn)"},"q24":{"question":"Which of the following sorting algorithms in its typical implementation gives best performance when applied on an array which is sorted or almost sorted (maximum 1 or two elements are misplaced).","hint":"None","answer_b":"Heap Sort","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Quick Sort","answer_d":"Insertion Sort","answer_c":"Merge Sort"},"q23":{"question":"Which of the following is not a stable sorting algorithm in its typical implementation.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Merge Sort","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Insertion Sort","answer_d":"Bubble Sort","answer_c":"Quick Sort"},"q26":{"question":"Consider a situation where swap operation is very costly. Which of the following sorting algorithms should be preferred so that the number of swap operations are minimized in general?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Selection Sort","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Heap Sort","answer_d":"Merge Sort","answer_c":"Insertion Sort"},"q25":{"question":"Given an unsorted array. The array has this property that every element in array is at most k distance from its position in sorted array where k is a positive integer smaller than size of array. Which sorting algorithm can be easily modified for sorting this array and what is the obtainable time complexity?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Heap Sort with time complexity O(nLogk)","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Insertion Sort with time complexity O(kn)","answer_d":"Merge Sort with time complexity O(kLogk)","answer_c":"Quick Sort with time complexity O(kLogk)"},"q28":{"question":"Suppose we are sorting an array of eight integers using quicksort, and we have just finished the first partitioning with the array looking like this: \n2  5  1  7  9  12  11  10 \n\n Which statement is correct?","hint":"None","answer_b":"The pivot could be the 7, but it is not the 9","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"The pivot could be either the 7 or the 9.","answer_d":"Neither the 7 nor the 9 is the pivot.","answer_c":"The pivot is not the 7, but it could be the 9"},"q27":{"question":"Which of the following is not true about comparison based sorting algorithms?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Any comparison based sorting algorithm can be made stable by using position as a criteria when two elements are compared","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"The minimum possible time complexity of a comparison based sorting algorithm is O(nLogn) for a random input array","answer_d":"Heap Sort is not a comparison based sorting algorithm.","answer_c":"Counting Sort is not a comparison based sorting algortihm"},"q29":{"question":"Suppose we are sorting an array of eight integers using heapsort, and we have just finished some heapify (either maxheapify or minheapify) operations. The array now looks like this: 16 14 15 10 12 27 28 How many heapify operations have been performed on root of heap?","hint":"None","answer_b":"2","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"1","answer_d":"5 or 6","answer_c":"3 or 4"},"q31":{"question":"What is the value of following recurrence.\n\n\nT(n) = T(n/4) + T(n/2) + cn^2\nT(1) = c\nT(0) = 0\nWhere c is a positive constant","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(n^2)","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(n^3)","answer_d":"O(nLogn)","answer_c":"O(n^2 Logn)"},"q30":{"question":"What is the best time complexity of bubble sort?","hint":"None","answer_b":"NlogN","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"N^2","answer_d":"N(logN)^2","answer_c":"N"},"q33":{"question":"What is the worst case time complexity of following implementation of subset sum problem.\n\n// Returns true if there is a subset of set[] with sun equal to given sum\nbool isSubsetSum(int set[], int n, int sum)\n{\n   // Base Cases\n   if (sum == 0)\n     return true;\n   if (n == 0 && sum != 0)\n     return false;\n \n   // If last element is greater than sum, then ignore it\n   if (set[n-1] > sum)\n     return isSubsetSum(set, n-1, sum);\n \n   /* else, check if sum can be obtained by any of the following\n      (a) including the last element\n      (b) excluding the last element   */\n   return isSubsetSum(set, n-1, sum) || \n          isSubsetSum(set, n-1, sum-set[n-1]);\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(n^2)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(n * 2^n)","answer_d":"O(2^n)","answer_c":"O(n^2 * 2^n)"},"q32":{"question":"What is the value of following recurrence. T(n) = 5T(n/5) + , T(1) = 1, T(0) = 0","hint":"None","answer_b":"Theta (n^2)","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Theta (n)","answer_d":"Theta (nLogn)","answer_c":"Theta (sqrt(n))"},"q35":{"question":"Consider the following recurrence:\n Which one of the following is true?\n (A) T(n) = (loglogn)\n (B) T(n) = (logn)\n (C) T(n) = (sqrt(n))\n (D) T(n) = (n)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q34":{"question":"Suppose T(n) = 2T(n/2) + n, T(0) = T(1) = 1 Which one of the following is false. ( GATE CS 2005)\n a) T(n) = O(n^2)\n b) T(n) = (nLogn)\n c) T(n) = (n^2)\n d) T(n) = O(nLogn)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q37":{"question":"The running time of the following algorithm\n\n  Procedure A(n)  \n  If n <= 2 return(1) else return A();\nis best described by","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(log n)","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(n)","answer_d":"O(1)","answer_c":"O(1og log n)"},"q36":{"question":"The running time of an algorithm is represented by the following recurrence relation:\n    if  n <= 3  then   T(n) = n\n    else T(n) = T(n/3) + cn\nWhich one of the following represents the time complexity of the algorithm?\n (A) (n)\n (B) (n log n)\n (C) (n^2)\n (D) (n^2log n)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q39":{"question":"The time complexity of the following C function is (assume n > 0 (GATE CS 2004)\n\nint recursive (mt n)\n{\n   if (n == 1)\n     return (1);\n   else\n     return (recursive (n-1) + recursive (n-1));\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"0(nlogn)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"0(n)","answer_d":"0(2^n)","answer_c":"0(n^2)"},"q38":{"question":"What is the time complexity of the following recursive function:\n\nint DoSomething (int n) \n{\n  if (n <= 2)\n    return 1;\n  else  \n    return (DoSomething (floor(sqrt(n))) + n);\n}\n(A) (n) \n (B) (nlogn)\n (C) (logn)\n (D) (loglogn)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q40":{"question":"Consider the following recurrence T(n) = 3T(n/5) + lgn * lgn What is the value of T(n)? \n (A) \n (B) \n (c) \n (D)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q42":{"question":"Consider the following recursive function fun(x, y). What is the value of fun(4, 3)\n\nint fun(int x, int y) \n{\n  if (x == 0)\n    return y;\n  return fun(x - 1,  x + y);\n} ","hint":"None","answer_b":"12","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"13","answer_d":"10","answer_c":"9"},"q41":{"question":"Predict output of following program\n\n#include <stdio.h>\n\nint fun(int n)\n{\n    if (n == 4)\n       return n;\n    else return 2*fun(n+1);\n}\n\n\nint main()\n{\n   printf(\"%d \", fun(2));\n   return 0;\n}\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"8","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"4","answer_d":"Runtime Error","answer_c":"16"},"q44":{"question":"What does the following function do?\n\nint fun(int x, int y)\n{\n    if (y == 0)   return 0;\n    return (x + fun(x, y-1));\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"x + x*y","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"x + y","answer_d":"xy","answer_c":"x*y"},"q43":{"question":"What does the following function print for n = 25?\n\nvoid fun(int n)\n{\n  if (n == 0)\n    return;\n\n  printf(\"%d\", n%2);\n  fun(n/2);\n}  ","hint":"None","answer_b":"10011","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"11001","answer_d":"00000","answer_c":"11111"},"q46":{"question":"Output of following program?\n\n#include<stdio.h>\nvoid print(int n)\n{\n    if (n > 4000)\n        return;\n    printf(\"%d \", n);\n    print(2*n);\n    printf(\"%d \", n);\n}\n\nint main()\n{\n    print(1000);\n    getchar();\n    return 0;\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"1000 2000 4000 4000 2000 1000","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"1000 2000 4000","answer_d":"1000 2000 2000 1000","answer_c":"1000 2000 4000 2000 1000"},"q45":{"question":"What does fun2() do in general?\n\nint fun(int x, int y)\n{\n    if (y == 0)   return 0;\n    return (x + fun(x, y-1));\n}\n\nint fun2(int a, int b)\n{\n    if (b == 0) return 1;\n    return fun(a, fun2(a, b-1));\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"x+x*y","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"x*y","answer_d":"yx","answer_c":"xy"},"q48":{"question":"Predict the output of following program\n\n#include <stdio.h>\nint f(int n)\n{\n    if(n <= 1)\n        return 1;\n    if(n%2 == 0)\n        return f(n/2);\n    return f(n/2) + f(n/2+1);\n}\n\n\nint main()\n{\n    printf(\"%d\", f(11));\n    return 0;\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"3","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Stack Overflow","answer_d":"5","answer_c":"4"},"q47":{"question":"What does the following function do?\n\nint fun(unsigned int n)\n{\n    if (n == 0 || n == 1)\n        return n;\n\n    if (n%3 != 0)\n        return 0;\n\n    return fun(n/3);\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"It returns 1 when n is a power of 3, otherwise returns 0","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"It returns 1 when n is a multiple of 3, otherwise returns 0","answer_d":"It returns 0 when n is a power of 3, otherwise returns 1","answer_c":"It returns 0 when n is a multiple of 3, otherwise returns 1"},"q49":{"question":"Consider the following recursive C function that takes two arguments\n\n unsigned int foo(unsigned int n, unsigned int r) {\n  if (n  > 0) return (n%r +  foo (n/r, r ));\n  else return 0;\n}\nWhat is the return value of the function foo when it is called as foo(345, 10) ?","hint":"None","answer_b":"12","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"345","answer_d":"3","answer_c":"5"},"q110":{"question":"Which of the following is not an in-place algorithm?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Selection sort","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Insertion sort","answer_d":"Heap sort","answer_c":"Merge sort"},"q51":{"question":"Which of the following standard algorithms is not Dynamic Programming based.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Floyd Warshall Algorithm for all pairs shortest paths","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Bellman\u2013Ford Algorithm for single source shortest path","answer_d":"Prim's Minimum Spanning Tree","answer_c":"0-1 Knapsack problem"},"q50":{"question":"Consider the same recursive C function that takes two arguments\n\nunsigned int foo(unsigned int n, unsigned int r) {\n  if (n  > 0) return (n%r +  foo (n/r, r ));\n  else return 0;\n}\nWhat is the return value of the function foo when it is called as foo(513, 2)?","hint":"None","answer_b":"8","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"9","answer_d":"2","answer_c":"5"},"q53":{"question":"An algorithm to find the length of the longest monotonically increasing sequence of numbers in an array A[0 :n-1] is given below. Let Li denote the length of the longest monotonically increasing sequence starting at index i in the array. \n \n Which of the following statements is TRUE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"The algorithm has a linear complexity and uses branch and bound paradigm","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"The algorithm uses dynamic programming paradigm","answer_d":"The algorithm uses divide and conquer paradigm.","answer_c":"The algorithm has a non-linear polynomial complexity and uses branch and bound paradigm"},"q52":{"question":"We use dynamic programming approach when","hint":"None","answer_b":"The solution has optimal substructure","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"We need an optimal solution","answer_d":"It's faster than Greedy","answer_c":"The given problem can be reduced to the 3-SAT problem"},"q55":{"question":"Four matrices M1, M2, M3 and M4 of dimensions pxq, qxr, rxs and sxt respectively can be multiplied is several ways with different number of total scalar multiplications. For example, when multiplied as ((M1 X M2) X (M3 X M4)), the total number of multiplications is pqr + rst + prt. When multiplied as (((M1 X M2) X M3) X M4), the total number of scalar multiplications is pqr + prs + pst. If p = 10, q = 100, r = 20, s = 5 and t = 80, then the number of scalar multiplications needed is","hint":"None","answer_b":"44000","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"248000","answer_d":"25000","answer_c":"19000"},"q104":{"question":"Suppose a polynomial time algorithm is discovered that correctly computes the largest clique in a given graph. In this scenario, which one of the following represents the correct Venn diagram of the complexity classes P, NP and NP Complete (NPC)?","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q54":{"question":"Kadane algorithm is used to find:","hint":"None","answer_b":"Maximum sum subarray in an array","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Maximum sum subsequence in an array","answer_d":"Maximum product subarray in an array","answer_c":"Maximum product subsequence in an array"},"q105":{"question":"Consider the decision problem 2CNFSAT defined as follows:","hint":"None","answer_b":"solvable in polynomial time by reduction to directed graph reachability.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"NP-Complete.","answer_d":"NP-hard, but not NP-complete.","answer_c":"solvable in constant time since any input instance is satisfiable."},"q57":{"question":"In the above question, which entry of the array X, if TRUE, implies that there is a subset whose elements sum to W?","hint":"None","answer_b":"X[n ,0]","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"X[1, W]","answer_d":"X[n -1, n]","answer_c":"X[n, W]"},"q106":{"question":"Let SHAM3 be the problem of finding a Hamiltonian cycle in a graph G = (V,E) with V divisible by 3 and DHAM3 be the problem of determining if a Hamiltonian cycle exists in such graphs. Which one of the following is true?","hint":"None","answer_b":"SHAM3 is NP-hard, but DHAM3 is not","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Both DHAM3 and SHAM3 are NP-hard","answer_d":"Neither DHAM3 nor SHAM3 is NP-hard","answer_c":"DHAM3 is NP-hard, but SHAM3 is not"},"q56":{"question":"The subset-sum problem is defined as follows. Given a set of n positive integers, S = {a1 ,a2 ,a3 ,\u2026,an} and positive integer W, is there a subset of S whose elements sum to W? A dynamic program for solving this problem uses a 2-dimensional Boolean array X, with n rows and W+1 columns. X[i, j],1 <= i <= n, 0 <= j <= W, is TRUE if and only if there is a subset of {a1 ,a2 ,...,ai} whose elements sum to j. Which of the following is valid for 2 <= i <= n and ai <= j <= W?","hint":"None","answer_b":"X[i, j] = X[i - 1, j] ∨ X[i - 1, j - ai]","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"X[i, j] = X[i - 1, j] ∨ X[i, j -ai]","answer_d":"X[i, j] = X[i - 1, j] ∧ X[i -1, j - ai]","answer_c":"X[i, j] = X[i - 1, j] ∧ X[i, j - ai]"},"q107":{"question":"In a complete k-ary tree, every internal node has exactly k children. The number of leaves in such a tree with n internal nodes is: (GATE CS 2005)","hint":"None","answer_b":"(n \u2013 1) k+ 1","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"nk","answer_d":"n( k \u2013 1)","answer_c":"n( k \u2013 1) + 1"},"q59":{"question":"Consider two strings A = \"qpqrr\" and B = \"pqprqrp\". Let x be the length of the longest common subsequence (not necessarily contiguous) between A and B and let y be the number of such longest common subsequences between A and B. Then x + 10y = ___.","hint":"None","answer_b":"23","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"33","answer_d":"34","answer_c":"43"},"q100":{"question":"The problem 3-SAT and 2-SAT are","hint":"None","answer_b":"both NP complete","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"both in P","answer_d":"undecidable and NP-complete respectively","answer_c":"NP-complete and in P respectively"},"q58":{"question":"A sub-sequence of a given sequence is just the given sequence with some elements (possibly none or all) left out. We are given two sequences X[m] and Y[n] of lengths m and n respectively, with indexes of X and Y starting from 0. We wish to find the length of the longest common sub-sequence(LCS) of X[m] and Y[n] as l(m,n), where an incomplete recursive definition for the function l(i,j) to compute the length of The LCS of X[m] and Y[n] is given below:\n\nl(i,j) = 0, if either i=0 or j=0\n       = expr1, if i,j > 0 and X[i-1] = Y[j-1]\n       = expr2, if i,j > 0 and X[i-1] != Y[j-1] ","hint":"None","answer_b":"expr1 ≡ l(i, j-1)","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"expr1 ≡ l(i-1, j) + 1","answer_d":"expr2 ≡ max(l(i-1,j-1),l(i,j))","answer_c":"expr2 ≡ max(l(i-1, j), l(i, j-1))"},"q101":{"question":"Which of the following statements are TRUE? (1) The problem of determining whether there exists a cycle in an undirected graph is in P. (2) The problem of determining whether there exists a cycle in an undirected graph is in NP. (3) If a problem A is NP-Complete, there exists a non-deterministic polynomial time algorithm to solve A.","hint":"None","answer_b":"1 and 3","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"1, 2 and 3","answer_d":"1 and 2","answer_c":"2 and 3"},"q102":{"question":"Which of the following is true about NP-Complete and NP-Hard problems.","hint":"None","answer_b":"The first problem that was proved as NP-complete was the circuit satisfiability problem.","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"If we want to prove that a problem X is NP-Hard, we take a known NP-Hard problem Y and reduce Y to X","answer_d":"All of the above","answer_c":"NP-complete is a subset of NP Hard"},"q103":{"question":"Which of the following statements are TRUE?\n\n1. The problem of determining whether there exists\n   a cycle in an undirected graph is in P.\n2. The problem of determining whether there exists\n   a cycle in an undirected graph is in NP.\n3. If a problem A is NP-Complete, there exists a \n   non-deterministic polynomial time algorithm to solve A. ","hint":"None","answer_b":"1 and 2 only","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"1, 2 and 3","answer_d":"1 and 3 only","answer_c":"2 and 3 only"},"q108":{"question":"Given 8 identical coins out of which one coin is heavy and a pan balance. How many minimum number of measurements are needed to find the heavy coin?","hint":"None","answer_b":"3","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"2","answer_d":"7","answer_c":"4"},"q109":{"question":"In a village, people build houses in the same side of the road. A thief plans to loot the village. He wants maximum amount of money without having any risk of getting caught. By some means, the villagers know that their adjacent house is being looted or not and thus they become alert. So the thief cannot loot contiguous two houses. Given that the thief knows the amount of money stored in each house and the road is straight and there is no turning, which is the most efficient algorithmic strategy to solve this problem?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Dynamic Programming","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Brute-force","answer_d":"Divide and Conquer","answer_c":"Backtracking"},"q1":{"question":"What is recurrence for worst case of QuickSort and what is the time complexity in Worst case?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Recurrence is T(n) = T(n-1) + O(n) and time complexity is O(n^2)","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Recurrence is T(n) = T(n-2) + O(n) and time complexity is O(n^2)","answer_d":"Recurrence is T(n) = T(n/10) + T(9n/10) + O(n) and time complexity is O(nLogn)","answer_c":"Recurrence is T(n) = 2T(n/2) + O(n) and time complexity is O(nLogn)"},"q2":{"question":"Suppose we have a O(n) time algorithm that finds median of an unsorted array. Now consider a QuickSort implementation where we first find median using the above algorithm, then use median as pivot. What will be the worst case time complexity of this modified QuickSort.","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(n^2)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(n^2 Logn)","answer_d":"O(nLogn)","answer_c":"O(n Logn Logn)"},"q3":{"question":"Given an unsorted array. The array has this property that every element in array is at most k distance from its position in sorted array where k is a positive integer smaller than size of array. Which sorting algorithm can be easily modified for sorting this array and what is the obtainable time complexity?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Heap Sort with time complexity O(nLogk)","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Insertion Sort with time complexity O(kn)","answer_d":"Merge Sort with time complexity O(kLogk)","answer_c":"Quick Sort with time complexity O(kLogk)"},"q4":{"question":"Which of the following is not true about comparison based sorting algorithms?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Any comparison based sorting algorithm can be made stable by using position as a criteria when two elements are compared","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"The minimum possible time complexity of a comparison based sorting algorithm is O(nLogn) for a random input array","answer_d":"Heap Sort is not a comparison based sorting algorithm.","answer_c":"Counting Sort is not a comparison based sorting algortihm"},"q5":{"question":"What is time complexity of fun()?\n\nint fun(int n)\n{\n  int count = 0;\n  for (int i = n; i > 0; i /= 2)\n     for (int j = 0; j < i; j++)\n        count += 1;\n  return count;\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(nLogn)","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(n^2)","answer_d":"O(nLognLogn)","answer_c":"O(n)"},"q6":{"question":"What is the time complexity of fun()?\n\nint fun(int n)\n{\n  int count = 0;\n  for (int i = 0; i < n; i++)\n     for (int j = i; j > 0; j--)\n        count = count + 1;\n  return count;\n} ","hint":"None","answer_b":"Theta (n^2)","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Theta (n)","answer_d":"Theta (nLognLogn)","answer_c":"Theta (n*Logn)"},"q7":{"question":"The recurrence relation capturing the optimal time of the Tower of Hanoi problem with n discs is. (GATE CS 2012)","hint":"None","answer_b":"T(n) = 2T(n \u2013 1) + n","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"T(n) = 2T(n \u2013 2) + 2","answer_d":"T(n) = 2T(n \u2013 1) + 1","answer_c":"T(n) = 2T(n/2) + 1"},"q8":{"question":"Let w(n) and A(n) denote respectively, the worst case and average case running time of an algorithm executed on an input of size n. which of the following is ALWAYS TRUE? (GATE CS 2012)\n (A) \n (B) \n (C) \n (D)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q9":{"question":"Which of the following is not O(n^2)?","hint":"None","answer_b":"n^1.98","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"(15^10) * n + 12099","answer_d":"(2^20) * n","answer_c":"n^3 / (sqrt(n))"},"q60":{"question":"Let A1, A2, A3, and A4 be four matrices of dimensions 10 x 5, 5 x 20, 20 x 10, and 10 x 5, respectively. The minimum number of scalar multiplications required to find the product A1A2A3A4 using the basic matrix multiplication method is","hint":"None","answer_b":"2000","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"1500","answer_d":"100","answer_c":"500"},"q62":{"question":"What does the following C expression do? x = (x<<1) + x + (x>>1);","hint":"None","answer_b":"Multiplies an integer with 3.5","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Multiplies an integer with 7","answer_d":"Multiplies an integer with 8","answer_c":"Multiplies an integer with 3"},"q61":{"question":"What is the return value of following function for arr[] = {9, 12, 2, 11, 2, 2, 10, 9, 12, 10, 9, 11, 2} and n is size of this array.\n\nint fun(int arr[], int n)\n{\n    int x = arr[0];\n    for (int i = 1; i < n; i++)\n        x = x ^ arr[i];\n    return x;\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"9","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"0","answer_d":"2","answer_c":"12"},"q64":{"question":"Given two arrays of numbers a1, a2, a3,...an and b1, b2, .. bn where each number is 0 or 1, the fastest algorithm to find the largest span(i, j) such that ai + ai+1, ....aj = bi + bi+1, .. bj. or report that there is not such span,","hint":"None","answer_b":"Takes O(n3) and Ω(n2.5) time in the key comparison model","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Takes O(n3) and Ω(2n) time if hashing is permitted","answer_d":"Takes O(√n) time only if the sum of the 2n elements is an even number","answer_c":"Takes θ(n) time and space"},"q63":{"question":"What does the following C expression do?\n x = x & (x-1) ","hint":"None","answer_b":"Makes x equals to 0","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Sets all bits as 1","answer_d":"Turns of the leftmost set bit","answer_c":"Turns of the rightmost set bit"},"q66":{"question":"Which of the following algorithms can be used to most efficiently determine the presence of a cycle in a given graph ?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Breadth First Search","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Depth First Search","answer_d":"Kruskal' Minimum Spanning Tree Algorithm","answer_c":"Prim's Minimum Spanning Tree Algorithm"},"q65":{"question":"Consider the following code snippet for checking whether a number is power of 2 or not.\n\n/* Incorrect function to check if x is power of 2*/\nbool isPowerOfTwo (unsigned int x) \n{ \n  return (!(x&(x-1))); \n} \nWhat is wrong with above function?","hint":"None","answer_b":"It works perfectly fine for all values of x.","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"It does reverse of what is required","answer_d":"It does not work for x = 1","answer_c":"It does not work for x = 0"},"q68":{"question":"What are the appropriate data structures for following algorithms?\n\n1) Breadth First Search                           \n2) Depth First Search                            \n3) Prim's Minimum Spanning Tree                 \n4) Kruskal' Minimum Spanning Tree                ","hint":"None","answer_b":"\n1) Queue\n2) Stack\n3) Priority Queue\n4) Union Find","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"\n1) Stack\n2) Queue\n3) Priority Queue\n4) Union Find","answer_d":"\n1) Priority Queue\n2) Queue\n3) Stack\n4) Union Find","answer_c":"\n1) Stack\n2) Queue\n3) Union Find\n4) Priority Queue "},"q67":{"question":"Traversal of a graph is different from tree because","hint":"None","answer_b":"DFS of a graph uses stack, but inorrder traversal of a tree is recursive","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"There can be a loop in graph so we must maintain a visited flag for every vertex","answer_d":"All of the above","answer_c":"BFS of a graph uses queue, but a time efficient BFS of a tree is recursive."},"q69":{"question":"The Breadth First Search algorithm has been implemented using the queue data structure. One possible order of visiting the nodes of the following graph is","hint":"None","answer_b":"NQMPOR","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"MNOPQR","answer_d":"QMNPOR","answer_c":"QMNPRO"}},"Data Structures":{"q71":{"question":"Consider a B+-tree in which the maximum number of keys in a node is 5. What is the minimum number of keys in any non-root node? (GATE CS 2010)","hint":"None","answer_b":"2","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"1","answer_d":"4","answer_c":"3"},"q70":{"question":"Which of the following data structures is best suited for efficient implementation of priority queue?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Linked List","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Array","answer_d":"Stack","answer_c":"Heap"},"q73":{"question":"B+ trees are preferred to binary trees in databases because (GATE CS 2000)","hint":"None","answer_b":"Disk access is much slower than memory access","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Disk capacities are greater than memory capacities","answer_d":"Disks are more reliable than memory","answer_c":"Disk data transfer rates are much less than memory data transfer rates"},"q72":{"question":"Which one of the following is a key factor for preferring B-trees to binary search trees for indexing database relations?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Database relations are sorted on the primary key","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Database relations have a large number of records","answer_d":"Data transfer form disks is in blocks.","answer_c":"B-trees require less memory than binary search trees"},"q75":{"question":"A B-tree of order 4 is built from scratch by 10 successive insertions. What is the maximum number of node splitting operations that may take place?","hint":"None","answer_b":"4","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"3","answer_d":"6","answer_c":"5"},"q74":{"question":"Which of the following is FALSE about B/B+ tree","hint":"None","answer_b":"Time complexity of search operation in B/B+ tree is better than Red Black Trees in general.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"B/B+ trees grow upward while Binary Search Trees grow downward.","answer_d":"A B/B+ tree is defined by a term minimum degree. And minimum degree depends on hard disk block size, key and address sizes.","answer_c":"Number of child pointers in a B/B+ tree node is always equals to number of keys in it plus one."},"q77":{"question":"The order of an internal node in a B+ tree index is the maximum number of children it can have. Suppose that a child pointer takes 6 bytes, the search field value takes 14 bytes, and the block size is 512 bytes. What is the order of the internal node?","hint":"None","answer_b":"25","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"24","answer_d":"27","answer_c":"26"},"q76":{"question":"The order of a leaf node in a tree B+ ? is the maximum number of (value, data record pointer) pairs it can hold. Given that the block size is 1K bytes, data record pointer is 7 bytes long, the value field is 9 bytes long and a block pointer is 6 bytes long, what is the order of the leaf node?","hint":"None","answer_b":"64","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"63","answer_d":"68","answer_c":"67"},"q79":{"question":"A B+ -tree index is to be built on the Name attribute of the relation STUDENT. Assume that all student names are of length 8 bytes, disk block are size 512 bytes, and index pointers are of size 4 bytes. Given this scenario, what would be the best choice of the degree (i.e. the number of pointers per node) of the B+ -tree?","hint":"None","answer_b":"42","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"16","answer_d":"44","answer_c":"43"},"q78":{"question":"Consider the following 2-3-4 tree (i.e., B-tree with a minimum degree of two) in which each data item is a letter. The usual alphabetical ordering of letters is used in constructing the tree. What is the result of inserting G in the above tree ?\n\nA) \n\nB) \n\nC) \n\nD) None of the above","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q80":{"question":"With reference to the B+ tree index of order 1 shown below, the minimum number of nodes (including the root node) that must be fetched in order to satisfy the following query: \u201cGet all records with a search key greater than or equal to 7 and less than 15\u201d is ________","hint":"None","answer_b":"5","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"4","answer_d":"7","answer_c":"6"},"q82":{"question":"Suppose we are sorting an array of eight integers using heapsort, and we have just finished some heapify (either maxheapify or minheapify) operations. The array now looks like this: 16 14 15 10 12 27 28 How many heapify operations have been performed on root of heap?","hint":"None","answer_b":"2","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"1","answer_d":"5 or 6","answer_c":"3 or 4"},"q81":{"question":"What is the time complexity of Build Heap operation. Build Heap is used to build a max(or min) binary heap from a given array. Build Heap is used in Heap Sort as a first step for sorting.","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(n^2)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(nLogn)","answer_d":"O(n)","answer_c":"O(Logn)"},"q84":{"question":"A 3-ary max heap is like a binary max heap, but instead of 2 children, nodes have 3 children. A 3-ary heap can be represented by an array as follows: The root is stored in the first location, a[0], nodes in the next level, from left to right, is stored from a[1] to a[3]. The nodes from the second level of the tree from left to right are stored from a[4] location onward. An item x can be inserted into a 3-ary heap containing n items by placing x in the location a[n] and pushing it up the tree to satisfy the heap property. Which one of the following is a valid sequence of elements in an array representing 3-ary max heap?","hint":"None","answer_b":"9, 6, 3, 1, 8, 5","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"1, 3, 5, 6, 8, 9","answer_d":"9, 5, 6, 8, 3, 1","answer_c":"9, 3, 6, 8, 5, 1"},"q83":{"question":"A max-heap is a heap where the value of each parent is greater than or equal to the values of its children. Which of the following is a max-heap? (GATE CS 2011)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q86":{"question":"Consider a binary max-heap implemented using an array. Which one of the following array represents a binary max-heap? (GATE CS 2009)","hint":"None","answer_b":"25,12,16,13,10,8,14","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"25,12,16,13,10,8,14","answer_d":"25,14,12,13,10,8,16","answer_c":"25,14,16,13,10,8,12"},"q85":{"question":"Suppose the elements 7, 2, 10 and 4 are inserted, in that order, into the valid 3- ary max heap found in the above question, Which one of the following is the sequence of items in the array representing the resultant heap?","hint":"None","answer_b":"10, 9, 8, 7, 6, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"10, 7, 9, 8, 3, 1, 5, 2, 6, 4","answer_d":"10, 8, 6, 9, 7, 2, 3, 4, 1, 5","answer_c":"10, 9, 4, 5, 7, 6, 8, 2, 1, 3"},"q88":{"question":"We have a binary heap on n elements and wish to insert n more elements (not necessarily one after another) into this heap. The total time required for this is (A) (logn) (B) (n) (C) (nlogn) (D) (n^2)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q87":{"question":"What is the content of the array after two delete operations on the correct answer to the previous question?","hint":"None","answer_b":"14,12,13,8,10","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"14,13,12,10,8","answer_d":"14,13,12,8,10","answer_c":"14,13,8,12,10"},"q89":{"question":"In a min-heap with n elements with the smallest element at the root, the 7th smallest element can be found in time a) (n log n) b) (n) c) (log n) d) (1) The question was not clear in original GATE exam. For clarity, assume that there are no duplicates in Min-Heap and accessing heap elements below root is allowed.","hint":"None","answer_b":"b","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"a","answer_d":"d","answer_c":"c"},"q91":{"question":"Following function is supposed to calculate the maximum depth or height of a Binary tree -- the number of nodes along the longest path from the root node down to the farthest leaf node.\n\nint maxDepth(struct node* node)\n{\n   if (node==NULL)\n       return 0;\n   else\n   {\n       /* compute the depth of each subtree */\n       int lDepth = maxDepth(node->left);\n       int rDepth = maxDepth(node->right);\n \n       /* use the larger one */\n       if (lDepth > rDepth)\n           return X;\n       else return Y;\n   }\n}\nWhat should be the values of X and Y so that the function works correctly?","hint":"None","answer_b":"X = lDepth + 1, Y = rDepth + 1","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"X = lDepth, Y = rDepth","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"X = lDepth - 1, Y = rDepth -1"},"q90":{"question":"In a binary max heap containing n numbers, the smallest element can be found in time (GATE CS 2006)","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(logn)","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"0(n)","answer_d":"0(1)","answer_c":"0(loglogn)"},"q93":{"question":"The inorder and preorder traversal of a binary tree are d b e a f c g and a b d e c f g, respectively. The postorder traversal of the binary tree is:","hint":"None","answer_b":"e d b g f c a","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"d e b f g c a","answer_d":"d e f g b c a","answer_c":"e d b f g c a"},"q92":{"question":"What is common in three different types of traversals (Inorder, Preorder and Postorder)?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Left subtree is always visited before right subtree","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Root is visited before right subtree","answer_d":"All of the above","answer_c":"Root is visited after left subtree"},"q95":{"question":"Which of the following pairs of traversals is not sufficient to build a binary tree from the given traversals?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Preorder and Postorder","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Preorder and Inorder","answer_d":"None of the Above","answer_c":"Inorder and Postorder"},"q94":{"question":"What does the following function do for a given binary tree?\n\nint fun(struct node *root)\n{\n   if (root == NULL)\n      return 0;\n   if (root->left == NULL && root->right == NULL)\n      return 0;\n   return 1 + fun(root->left) + fun(root->right);\n}","hint":"None","answer_b":"Counts internal nodes","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Counts leaf nodes","answer_d":"Return diameter where diameter is number of edges on the longest path between any two nodes.","answer_c":"Returns height where height is defined as number of edges on the path from root to deepest node"},"q97":{"question":"Which traversal of tree resembles the breadth first search of the graph?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Inorder","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Preorder","answer_d":"Level order","answer_c":"Postorder"},"q96":{"question":"Consider two binary operators ' ' and '' with the precedence of operator being lower than that of the operator. Operator is right associative while operator is left associative. Which one of the following represents the parse tree for expression (7 3 ­ 4 ­ 3 2)? (GATE CS 2011)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q11":{"question":"Following is C like pseudo code of a function that takes a Queue as an argument, and uses a stack S to do processing.\n\nvoid fun(Queue *Q)\n{\n    Stack S;  // Say it creates an empty stack S\n\n    // Run while Q is not empty\n    while (!isEmpty(Q))\n    {\n        // deQueue an item from Q and push the dequeued item to S\n        push(&S, deQueue(Q));\n    }\n\n    // Run while Stack S is not empty\n    while (!isEmpty(&S))\n    {\n      // Pop an item from S and enqueue the poppped item to Q\n      enQueue(Q, pop(&S));\n    }\n}\nWhat does the above function do in general?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Keeps the Q same as it was before the call","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Removes the last from Q","answer_d":"Reverses the Q","answer_c":"Makes Q empty"},"q99":{"question":"Which of the following cannot generate the full binary tree?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Inorder and Postorder","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Inorder and Preorder","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"Preorder and Postorder"},"q10":{"question":"To evaluate an expression without any embedded function calls:","hint":"None","answer_b":"Two stacks are needed","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"One stack is enough","answer_d":"A Turing machine is needed in the general case","answer_c":"As many stacks as the height of the expression tree are needed"},"q98":{"question":"Which of the following tree traversal uses a queue data structure?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Inorder","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Preorder","answer_d":"Level order","answer_c":"Postorder"},"q13":{"question":"How many stacks are needed to implement a queue. Consider the situation where no other data structure like arrays, linked list is available to you.","hint":"None","answer_b":"2","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"1","answer_d":"4","answer_c":"3"},"q12":{"question":"Which one of the following is an application of Queue Data Structure?","hint":"None","answer_b":"When data is transferred asynchronously (data not necessarily received at same rate as sent) between two processes","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"When a resource is shared among multiple consumers.","answer_d":"All of the above","answer_c":"Load Balancing"},"q15":{"question":"A priority queue can efficiently implemented using which of the following data structures? Assume that the number of insert and peek (operation to see the current highest priority item) and extraction (remove the highest priority item) operations are almost same.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Linked List","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Array","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"Heap Data Structures like Binary Heap, Fibonacci Heap"},"q14":{"question":"How many queues are needed to implement a stack. Consider the situation where no other data structure like arrays, linked list is available to you.","hint":"None","answer_b":"2","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"1","answer_d":"4","answer_c":"3"},"q17":{"question":"Suppose a circular queue of capacity (n \u2013 1) elements is implemented with an array of n elements. Assume that the insertion and deletion operation are carried out using REAR and FRONT as array index variables, respectively. Initially, REAR = FRONT = 0. The conditions to detect queue full and queue empty are","hint":"None","answer_b":"Full: (REAR+1) mod n == FRONT, empty: (FRONT+1) mod n == REAR","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Full: (REAR+1) mod n == FRONT, empty: REAR == FRONT","answer_d":"Full: (FRONT+1) mod n == REAR, empty: REAR == FRONT","answer_c":"Full: REAR == FRONT, empty: (REAR+1) mod n == FRONT"},"q16":{"question":"Which of the following is true about linked list implementation of queue?","hint":"None","answer_b":"In push operation, if new nodes are inserted at the end, then in pop operation, nodes must be removed from the beginning.","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"In push operation, if new nodes are inserted at the beginning of linked list, then in pop operation, nodes must be removed from end.","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"Both of the above"},"q19":{"question":"An implementation of a queue Q, using two stacks S1 and S2, is given below:\n\nvoid insert(Q, x) {\n   push (S1, x);\n}\n \nvoid delete(Q){\n   if(stack-empty(S2)) then \n      if(stack-empty(S1)) then {\n          print(\u201cQ is empty\u201d);\n          return;\n      }\n      else while (!(stack-empty(S1))){\n          x=pop(S1);\n          push(S2,x);\n      }\n   x=pop(S2);\n}\nLet n insert and m (<=n) delete operations be performed in an arbitrary order on an empty queue Q. Let x and y be the number of push and pop operations performed respectively in the process. Which one of the following is true for all m and n?","hint":"None","answer_b":"n+m <= x < 2n and 2m<= y <= 2n","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"n+m <= x < 2n and 2m <= y <= n+m","answer_d":"2m <= x <2n and 2m <= y <= 2n","answer_c":"2m <= x < 2n and 2m <= y <= n+m"},"q18":{"question":"A Priority-Queue is implemented as a Max-Heap. Initially, it has 5 elements. The level-order traversal of the heap is given below: 10, 8, 5, 3, 2 Two new elements \u201d1\u2018 and \u201d7\u2018 are inserted in the heap in that order. The level-order traversal of the heap after the insertion of the elements is:","hint":"None","answer_b":"10, 8, 7, 2, 3, 1, 5","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"10, 8, 7, 5, 3, 2, 1","answer_d":"10, 8, 7, 3, 2, 1, 5","answer_c":"10, 8, 7, 1, 2, 3, 5"},"q20":{"question":"Consider the following operation along with Enqueue and Dequeue operations on queues, where k is a global parameter.\n\nMultiDequeue(Q){\n   m = k\n   while (Q is not empty and m  > 0) {\n      Dequeue(Q)\n      m = m - 1\n   }\n}\nWhat is the worst case time complexity of a sequence of n MultiDequeue() operations on an initially empty queue? (GATE CS 2013) (A) (B) (C) (D)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q22":{"question":"In delete operation of BST, we need inorder successor (or predecessor) of a node when the node to be deleted has both left and right child as non-empty. Which of the following is true about inorder successor needed in delete operation?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Inorder successor is always either a leaf node or a node with empty left child","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Inorder Successor is always a leaf node","answer_d":"Inorder successor is always either a leaf node or a node with empty right child","answer_c":"Inorder successor may be an ancestor of the node"},"q21":{"question":"What is the worst case time complexity for search, insert and delete operations in a general Binary Search Tree?","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(Logn) for all","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(n) for all","answer_d":"O(Logn) for search, and O(n) for insert and delete","answer_c":"O(Logn) for search and insert, and O(n) for delete"},"q24":{"question":"How many distinct binary search trees can be created out of 4 distinct keys?","hint":"None","answer_b":"14","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"4","answer_d":"42","answer_c":"24"},"q23":{"question":"We are given a set of n distinct elements and an unlabeled binary tree with n nodes. In how many ways can we populate the tree with the given set so that it becomes a binary search tree? (GATE CS 2011)","hint":"None","answer_b":"1","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"0","answer_d":"(1/(n+1)).2nCn","answer_c":"n!"},"q26":{"question":"Suppose the numbers 7, 5, 1, 8, 3, 6, 0, 9, 4, 2 are inserted in that order into an initially empty binary search tree. The binary search tree uses the usual ordering on natural numbers. What is the in-order traversal sequence of the resultant tree?","hint":"None","answer_b":"0 2 4 3 1 6 5 9 8 7","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"7 5 1 0 3 2 4 6 8 9","answer_d":"9 8 6 4 2 3 0 1 5 7","answer_c":"0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9"},"q25":{"question":"Which of the following traversal outputs the data in sorted order in a BST?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Inorder","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Preorder","answer_d":"Level order","answer_c":"Postorder"},"q28":{"question":"The preorder traversal sequence of a binary search tree is 30, 20, 10, 15, 25, 23, 39, 35, 42. Which one of the following is the postorder traversal sequence of the same tree?","hint":"None","answer_b":"15, 10, 25, 23, 20, 42, 35, 39, 30","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"10, 20, 15, 23, 25, 35, 42, 39, 30","answer_d":"15, 10, 23, 25, 20, 35, 42, 39, 30","answer_c":"15, 20, 10, 23, 25, 42, 35, 39, 30"},"q27":{"question":"The following numbers are inserted into an empty binary search tree in the given order: 10, 1, 3, 5, 15, 12, 16. What is the height of the binary search tree (the height is the maximum distance of a leaf node from the root)? (GATE CS 2004)","hint":"None","answer_b":"3","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"2","answer_d":"6","answer_c":"4"},"q29":{"question":"Consider the following Binary Search Tree\n\n\n               10\n             /    \n            5      20\n           /      /             \n          4     15    30\n               /  \n              11       \nIf we randomly search one of the keys present in above BST, what would be the expected number of comparisons?","hint":"None","answer_b":"2.25","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"2.75","answer_d":"3.25","answer_c":"2.57"},"q31":{"question":"The worst case running time to search for an element in a balanced in a binary search tree with n2^n elements is \n (A) \n (B) \n (C) \n (D)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q30":{"question":"Which of the following traversals is sufficient to construct BST from given traversals 1) Inorder 2) Preorder 3) Postorder","hint":"None","answer_b":"Either 2 or 3 is sufficient","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Any one of the given three traversals is sufficient","answer_d":"1 and 3","answer_c":"2 and 3"},"q33":{"question":"What is the worst case possible height of AVL tree?","hint":"None","answer_b":"1.44log n \n Assume base of log is 2","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"2Logn \n Assume base of log is 2","answer_d":"Theta(n)","answer_c":"Depends upon implementation"},"q32":{"question":"What is the maximum height of any AVL-tree with 7 nodes? Assume that the height of a tree with a single node is 0.","hint":"None","answer_b":"3","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"2","answer_d":"5","answer_c":"4"},"q35":{"question":"Consider the following AVL tree.\n\n         60\n      /       \n    20      100\n           /   \n         80    120     \nWhich of the following is updated AVL tree after insertion of 70\n\nA\n        70\n      /      \n    60      100\n   /       /    \n 20       80    120 \n\nB\n        100\n      /      \n    60      120\n   /       /  \n 20   70   80   \n\n\nC\n        80\n      /      \n    60      100\n   /         \n 20   70      120\n\nD\n        80\n      /      \n    60      100\n   /       /   \n 20      70    120  ","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q34":{"question":"Which of the following is AVL Tree?\n\nA\n        100\n     /      \n    50       200\n   /           \n 10            300\n\n\nB\n           100\n       /       \n     50        200\n    /        /     \n  10       150     300\n /\n5\n\n\nC\n            100\n       /          \n     50            200\n    /            /     \n  10    60       150     300\n /                         \n5                   180       400","hint":"None","answer_b":"A and C","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Only A","answer_d":"Only B","answer_c":"A, B and C"},"q37":{"question":"Consider the following left-rotate and right-rotate functions commonly used in self-adjusting BSTs\n\nT1, T2 and T3 are subtrees of the tree rooted with y (on left side) \nor x (on right side)           \n                y                               x\n               /      Right Rotation          /  \n              x   T3   \u2013 - \u2013 - \u2013 - \u2013 >        T1   y \n             /        < - - - - - - -            / \n            T1  T2     Left Rotation            T2  T3\nWhich of the following is tightest upper bound for left-rotate and right-rotate operations.","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(Logn)","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(1)","answer_d":"O(n)","answer_c":"O(LogLogn)"},"q36":{"question":"Which of the following is a self-adjusting or self-balancing Binary Search Tree","hint":"None","answer_b":"AVL Tree","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Splay Tree","answer_d":"All of the above","answer_c":"Red Black Tree"},"q39":{"question":"Which of the following is true about Red Black Trees?","hint":"None","answer_b":"At least one children of every black node is red","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"The path from the root to the furthest leaf is no more than twice as long as the path from the root to the nearest leaf","answer_d":"A leaf node may be red","answer_c":"Root may be red"},"q38":{"question":"Which of the following is true","hint":"None","answer_b":"Heights of AVL and Red-Black trees are generally same, but AVL Trees may cause more rotations during insertion and deletion.","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"The AVL trees are more balanced compared to Red Black Trees, but they may cause more rotations during insertion and deletion.","answer_d":"Heights of AVL and Red-Black trees are generally same, but Red Black rees may cause more rotations during insertion and deletion.","answer_c":"Red Black trees are more balanced compared to AVL Trees, but may cause more rotations during insertion and deletion."},"q40":{"question":"Which of the following is true about AVL and Red Black Trees?","hint":"None","answer_b":"In both AVL and Red Black insert operations, we traverse only once from root to newly inserted node,","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"In AVL tree insert() operation, we first traverse from root to newly inserted node and then from newly inserted node to root. While in Red Black tree insert(), we only traverse once from root to newly inserted node.","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"In both AVL and Red Black insert operations, we traverse twiceL first traverse root to newly inserted node and then from newly inserted node to root."},"q42":{"question":"The degree sequence of a simple graph is the sequence of the degrees of the nodes in the graph in decreasing order. Which of the following sequences can not be the degree sequence of any graph? \nI. 7, 6, 5, 4, 4, 3, 2, 1\nII. 6, 6, 6, 6, 3, 3, 2, 2\nIII. 7, 6, 6, 4, 4, 3, 2, 2\nIV. 8, 7, 7, 6, 4, 2, 1, 1 ","hint":"None","answer_b":"III and IV","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"I and II","answer_d":"II and IV","answer_c":"IV only"},"q41":{"question":"Which of the following is an advantage of adjacency list representation over adjacency matrix representation of a graph?","hint":"None","answer_b":"DFS and BSF can be done in O(V + E) time for adjacency list representation. These operations take O(V^2) time in adjacency matrix representation. Here is V and E are number of vertices and edges respectively.","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"In adjacency list representation, space is saved for sparse graphs.","answer_d":"All of the above","answer_c":"Adding a vertex in adjacency list representation is easier than adjacency matrix representation."},"q44":{"question":"The most efficient algorithm for finding the number of connected components in an undirected graph on n vertices and m edges has time complexity. (A) (n) (B) (m) (C) (m + n) (D) (mn)","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q43":{"question":"The time complexity of computing the transitive closure of a binary relation on a set of n elements is known to be:","hint":"None","answer_b":"O(nLogn)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"O(n)","answer_d":"O(n^3)","answer_c":"O(n ^ (3/2))"},"q46":{"question":"How many undirected graphs (not necessarily connected) can be constructed out of a given set V= {V 1, V 2,\u2026V n} of n vertices ?","hint":"None","answer_b":"2^n","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"n(n-l)/2","answer_d":"2^(n(n-1)/2)","answer_c":"n!"},"q45":{"question":"Consider an undirected unweighted graph G. Let a breadth-first traversal of G be done starting from a node r. Let d(r, u) and d(r, v) be the lengths of the shortest paths from r to u and v respectively, in G. lf u is visited before v during the breadth-first traversal, which of the following statements is correct? (GATE CS 2001)","hint":"None","answer_b":"d(r, u) > d(r, v)","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"d(r, u) < d (r, v)","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"d(r, u) <= d (r, v)"},"q48":{"question":"Consider an undirected random graph of eight vertices. The probability that there is an edge between a pair of vertices is 1/2. What is the expected number of unordered cycles of length three?","hint":"None","answer_b":"1","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"1/8","answer_d":"8","answer_c":"7"},"q47":{"question":"Which of the following statements is/are TRUE for an undirected graph? P: Number of odd degree vertices is even Q: Sum of degrees of all vertices is even","hint":"None","answer_b":"Q Only","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"P Only","answer_d":"Neither P nor Q","answer_c":"Both P and Q"},"q49":{"question":"Given an undirected graph G with V vertices and E edges, the sum of the degrees of all vertices is","hint":"None","answer_b":"2E","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"E","answer_d":"2V","answer_c":"V"},"q51":{"question":"A hash table of length 10 uses open addressing with hash function h(k)=k mod 10, and linear probing. After inserting 6 values into an empty hash table, the table is as shown below. \n \n Which one of the following choices gives a possible order in which the key values could have been inserted in the table?","hint":"None","answer_b":"34, 42, 23, 52, 33, 46","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"46, 42, 34, 52, 23, 33","answer_d":"42, 46, 33, 23, 34, 52","answer_c":"46, 34, 42, 23, 52, 33"},"q50":{"question":"How many undirected graphs (not necessarily connected) can be constructed out of a given set V = {v1, v2, ... vn} of n vertices?","hint":"None","answer_b":"2n","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"n(n-1)/2","answer_d":"2n(n-1)/2","answer_c":"n!"},"q53":{"question":"The keys 12, 18, 13, 2, 3, 23, 5 and 15 are inserted into an initially empty hash table of length 10 using open addressing with hash function h(k) = k mod 10 and linear probing. What is the resultant hash table?","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q52":{"question":"How many different insertion sequences of the key values using the same hash function and linear probing will result in the hash table shown above?","hint":"None","answer_b":"20","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"10","answer_d":"40","answer_c":"30"},"q55":{"question":"Consider a hash table of size seven, with starting index zero, and a hash function (3x + 4)mod7. Assuming the hash table is initially empty, which of the following is the contents of the table when the sequence 1, 3, 8, 10 is inserted into the table using closed hashing? Note that \u2018_\u2019 denotes an empty location in the table.","hint":"None","answer_b":"1, 8, 10, _, _, _, 3","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"8, _, _, _, _, _, 10","answer_d":"1, 10, 8, _, _, _, 3","answer_c":"1, _, _, _, _, _,3"},"q54":{"question":"Consider a hash table of size seven, with starting index zero, and a hash function (3x + 4)mod7. Assuming the hash table is initially empty, which of the following is the contents of the table when the sequence 1, 3, 8, 10 is inserted into the table using closed hashing? Note that \u2018_\u2019 denotes an empty location in the table.","hint":"None","answer_b":"1, 8, 10, _, _, _, 3","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"8, _, _, _, _, _, 10","answer_d":"1, 10, 8, _, _, _, 3","answer_c":"1, _, _, _, _, _,3"},"q57":{"question":"Consider a hash table with 100 slots. Collisions are resolved using chaining. Assuming simple uniform hashing, what is the probability that the first 3 slots are unfilled after the first 3 insertions?","hint":"None","answer_b":"(99 × 98 × 97)/1003","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"(97 × 97 × 97)/1003","answer_d":"(97 × 96 × 95)/(3! × 1003)","answer_c":"(97 × 96 × 95)/1003"},"q56":{"question":"Given the following input (4322, 1334, 1471, 9679, 1989, 6171, 6173, 4199) and the hash function x mod 10, which of the following statements are true? i. 9679, 1989, 4199 hash to the same value ii. 1471, 6171 has to the same value iii. All elements hash to the same value iv. Each element hashes to a different value (GATE CS 2004)","hint":"None","answer_b":"ii only","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"i only","answer_d":"iii or iv","answer_c":"i and ii only"},"q59":{"question":"Given a hash table T with 25 slots that stores 2000 elements, the load factor α for T is __________","hint":"None","answer_b":"0.0125","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"80","answer_d":"1.25","answer_c":"8000"},"q100":{"question":"Consider the following C program segment\n\nstruct CellNode\n{\n  struct CelINode *leftchild;\n  int element;\n  struct CelINode *rightChild;\n}\n\nint Dosomething(struct CelINode *ptr)\n{\n    int value = 0;\n    if (ptr != NULL)\n    {\n      if (ptr->leftChild != NULL)\n        value = 1 + DoSomething(ptr->leftChild);\n      if (ptr->rightChild != NULL)\n        value = max(value, 1 + DoSomething(ptr->rightChild));\n    }\n    return (value);\n}\nThe value returned by the function DoSomething when a pointer to the root of a non-empty tree is passed as argument is (GATE CS 2004)","hint":"None","answer_b":"The number of nodes in the tree","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"The number of leaf nodes in the tree","answer_d":"The height of the tree","answer_c":"The number of internal nodes in the tree"},"q58":{"question":"Which one of the following hash functions on integers will distribute keys most uniformly over 10 buckets numbered 0 to 9 for i ranging from 0 to 2020?","hint":"None","answer_b":"h(i) =i3 mod 10","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"h(i) =i2 mod 10","answer_d":"h(i) = (12 ∗ i) mod 10","answer_c":"h(i) = (11 ∗ i2) mod 10"},"q1":{"question":"Following is C like pseudo code of a function that takes a number as an argument, and uses a stack S to do processing.\n\nvoid fun(int n)\n{\n    Stack S;  // Say it creates an empty stack S\n    while (n > 0)\n    {\n      // This line pushes the value of n%2 to stack S\n      push(&S, n%2);\n\n      n = n/2;\n    }\n\n    // Run while Stack S is not empty\n    while (!isEmpty(&S))\n      printf(\"%d \", pop(&S)); // pop an element from S and print it\n}\nWhat does the above function do in general?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Prints binary representation of n","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Prints binary representation of n in reverse order","answer_d":"Prints the value of Logn in reverse order","answer_c":"Prints the value of Logn"},"q2":{"question":"Which one of the following is an application of Stack Data Structure?","hint":"None","answer_b":"The stock span problem","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Managing function calls","answer_d":"All of the above","answer_c":"Arithmetic expression evaluation"},"q3":{"question":"Which of the following is true about linked list implementation of stack?","hint":"None","answer_b":"In push operation, if new nodes are inserted at the end, then in pop operation, nodes must be removed from the beginning.","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"In push operation, if new nodes are inserted at the beginning of linked list, then in pop operation, nodes must be removed from end.","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"Both of the above"},"q4":{"question":"Consider the following pseudocode that uses a stack\n\n   declare a stack of characters\n   while ( there are more characters in the word to read )\n   {\n      read a character\n      push the character on the stack\n   }\n   while ( the stack is not empty )\n   {\n      pop a character off the stack\n      write the character to the screen\n   }\nWhat is output for input \"geeksquiz\"?","hint":"None","answer_b":"ziuqskeeg","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"geeksquizgeeksquiz","answer_d":"ziuqskeegziuqskeeg","answer_c":"geeksquiz"},"q5":{"question":"Following is an incorrect pseudocode for the algorithm which is supposed to determine whether a sequence of parentheses is balanced:\n\n   declare a character stack \n   while ( more input is available)\n   {\n      read a character\n      if ( the character is a '(' ) \n         push it on the stack\n      else if ( the character is a ')' and the stack is not empty )\n         pop a character off the stack\n      else\n         print \"unbalanced\" and exit\n    }\n    print \"balanced\"\nWhich of these unbalanced sequences does the above code think is balanced? Source: http://www.cs.colorado.edu/~main/questions/chap07q.html","hint":"None","answer_b":"())(()","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"((())","answer_d":"(()))()","answer_c":"(()()))"},"q6":{"question":"The following postfix expression with single digit operands is evaluated using a stack:\n\n              8 2 3 ^ / 2 3 * + 5 1 * - \nNote that ^ is the exponentiation operator. The top two elements of the stack after the first * is evaluated are:","hint":"None","answer_b":"5, 7","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"6, 1","answer_d":"1, 5","answer_c":"3, 2"},"q7":{"question":"Let S be a stack of size n >= 1. Starting with the empty stack, suppose we push the first n natural numbers in sequence, and then perform n pop operations. Assume that Push and Pop operation take X seconds each, and Y seconds elapse between the end of one such stack operation and the start of the next operation. For m >= 1, define the stack-life of m as the time elapsed from the end of Push(m) to the start of the pop operation that removes m from S. The average stack-life of an element of this stack is","hint":"None","answer_b":"3Y + 2X","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"n(X+ Y)","answer_d":"Y + 2X","answer_c":"n(X + Y)-X"},"q8":{"question":"A single array A[1..MAXSIZE] is used to implement two stacks. The two stacks grow from opposite ends of the array. Variables top1 and top2 (topl< top 2) point to the location of the topmost element in each of the stacks. If the space is to be used efficiently, the condition for \u201cstack full\u201d is (GATE CS 2004)","hint":"None","answer_b":"top1 + top2 = MAXSIZE","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"(top1 = MAXSIZE/2) and (top2 = MAXSIZE/2+1)","answer_d":"top1= top2 -1","answer_c":"(top1= MAXSIZE/2) or (top2 = MAXSIZE)"},"q9":{"question":"Assume that the operators +, -, × are left associative and ^ is right associative. The order of precedence (from highest to lowest) is ^, x , +, -. The postfix expression corresponding to the infix expression a + b × c - d ^ e ^ f is","hint":"None","answer_b":"abc × + de ^ f ^ -","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"abc × + def ^ ^ -","answer_d":"- + a × bc ^ ^ def","answer_c":"ab + c × d - e ^ f ^"},"q60":{"question":"Which of the following statement(s) is TRUE?\n1. A hash function takes a message of arbitrary length and generates a fixed length code.\n2. A hash function takes a message of fixed length and generates a code of variable length.\n3. A hash function may give the same hash value for distinct messages.\n  ","hint":"None","answer_b":"II and III only","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"I only","answer_d":"II only","answer_c":"I and III only"},"q62":{"question":"Which data structure is used in redo-undo feature?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Queue","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Stack","answer_d":"Graph","answer_c":"Tree"},"q61":{"question":"Which data structure is used for balancing of symbols?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Queue","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Stack","answer_d":"Graph","answer_c":"Tree"},"q64":{"question":"The best data structure to check whether an arithmetic expression has balanced parentheses is a (GATE CS 2004)","hint":"None","answer_b":"stack","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"queue","answer_d":"list","answer_c":"tree"},"q63":{"question":"Which data structure is most efficient to find the top 10 largest items out of 1 million items stored in file?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Max heap","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Min heap","answer_d":"Sorted array","answer_c":"BST"},"q66":{"question":"The most appropriate matching for the following pairs\nX: depth first search            1: heap\nY: breadth-first search          2: queue\nZ: sorting                       3: stack\nis (GATE CS 2000):","hint":"None","answer_b":"X\u20143 Y\u20141 Z-2","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"X\u20141 Y\u20142 Z-3","answer_d":"X\u20142 Y\u20143 Z-1","answer_c":"X\u20143 Y\u20142 Z-1"},"q65":{"question":"A data structure is required for storing a set of integers such that each of the following operations can be done in (log n) time, where n is the number of elements in the set.\n\n   o\tDelection of the smallest element \n   o\tInsertion of an element if it is not already present in the set\nWhich of the following data structures can be used for this purpose?","hint":"None","answer_b":"A balanced binary search tree can be used but not a heap","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A heap can be used but not a balanced binary search tree","answer_d":"Neither balanced binary search tree nor heap can be used","answer_c":"Both balanced binary search tree and heap can be used"},"q68":{"question":"Which data structure is best suited for converting recursive implementation to iterative implementation of an algorithm?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Stack","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Queue","answer_d":"Graph","answer_c":"Tree"},"q67":{"question":"Which among the following data structures is best suited for storing very large numbers (numbers that cannot be stored in long long int). Following are the operations needed for these large numbers.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Linked List","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Array","answer_d":"Hash","answer_c":"Binary Tree"},"q69":{"question":"Consider a situation where a client receives packets from a server. There may be differences in speed of the client and the server. Which data structure is best suited for synchronization?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Queue","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Circular Linked List","answer_d":"Priority Queue","answer_c":"Stack"}},"Comp Theory":{"q31":{"question":"Which of the following is/are undecidable?","hint":"None","answer_b":"3 and 4 only","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"3 only","answer_d":"2 and 3 only","answer_c":"1, 2 and 3 only"},"q30":{"question":"Nobody knows yet if P = NP. Consider the language L defined as follows : Which of the following statements is true ?","hint":"None","answer_b":"L is recursively enumerable but not recursive","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"L is recursive","answer_d":"Whether L is recursive or not will be known after we find out if P = NP","answer_c":"L is not recursively enumerable"},"q11":{"question":"Consider the following languages. Which one of the following statements is FALSE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"L1 intersection L2 is context-free.","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"L2 is context-free.","answer_d":"Complement of L1 is context-free but not regular.","answer_c":"Complement of L2 is recursive."},"q33":{"question":"Which of the following are decidable?\nI. Whether the intersection of two regular languages is infinite\nII. Whether a given context-free language is regular\nIII. Whether two push-down automata accept the same language\nIV. Whether a given grammar is context-free","hint":"None","answer_b":"I and IV","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"I and II","answer_d":"II and IV","answer_c":"II and III"},"q10":{"question":"Which one of the following is FALSE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Every NFA can be converted to an equivalent PDA.","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"There is unique minimal DFA for every regular language","answer_d":"Every nondeterministic PDA can be converted to an equivalent deterministic PDA.","answer_c":"Complement of every context-free language is recursive."},"q32":{"question":"Which of the following problems are decidable?","hint":"None","answer_b":"1, 2","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"1, 2, 3, 4","answer_d":"3, 4","answer_c":"2, 3, 4"},"q13":{"question":"1) Let P be a regular language and Q be context-free language such that Q P. (For example, let P be the language represented by the regular expression p*q* and Q be {pnqn|n N}). Then which of the following is ALWAYS regular? (A) P Q (B) P - Q (C) * - P (D) * - Q","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q35":{"question":"Let <M> be the encoding of a Turing machine as a string over ∑= {0, 1}.  Let L = { <M> |M is a Turing machine that accepts a string of length 2014 }. Then, L is","hint":"None","answer_b":"undecidable but recursively enumerable","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"decidable and recursively enumerable","answer_d":"decidable but not recursively enumerable","answer_c":"undecidable and not recursively enumerable"},"q12":{"question":"Which of the following pairs have DIFFERENT expressive power?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Deterministic push down automata(DPDA)and Non-deterministic push down automata(NPDA)","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Deterministic finite automata(DFA) and Non-deterministic finite automata(NFA)","answer_d":"Single-tape Turing machine and multi-tape Turing machine","answer_c":"Deterministic single-tape Turing machine and Non-deterministic single-tape Turing machine"},"q34":{"question":"Which of the following problems is undecidable? [2007]","hint":"None","answer_b":"Ambiguity problem for CFGs.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Membership problem for CFGs","answer_d":"Equivalence problem for FSAs.","answer_c":"Finiteness problem for FSAs."},"q15":{"question":"Consider the languages L1 = {0i1j | i != j}. L2 = {0i1j | i = j}. L3 = {0i1j | i = 2j+1}. L4 = {0i1j | i != 2j}.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Only L2 and L3 are context free","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Only L2 is context free","answer_d":"All are context free","answer_c":"Only L1 and L2 are context free"},"q37":{"question":"Consider three decision problems P1, P2 and P3. It is known that P1 is decidable and P2 is undecidable. Which one of the following is TRUE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"P3 is undecidable if P3 is reducible to P2","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"P3 is decidable if P1 is reducible to P3","answer_d":"P3 is decidable if P3 is reducible to P2's complement","answer_c":"P3 is undecidable if P2 is reducible to P3"},"q14":{"question":"2) Consider the language L1,L2,L3 as given below. L1={ | p,q N} L2={ | p,q N and p=q} L3={ | p,q,r N and p=q=r} Which of the following statements is NOT TRUE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"L1 is a regular language","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Push Down Automata (PDA) can be used to recognize L1 and L2","answer_d":"Turing machine can be used to recognize all the three languages","answer_c":"All the three languages are context free"},"q36":{"question":"Which of the following problems is undecidable?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Deciding if a given string is generated by a given context-free grammar.","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Deciding if a given context-free grammar is ambiguous.","answer_d":"Deciding if the language generated by a given context-free grammar is finite.","answer_c":"Deciding if the language generated by a given context-free grammar is empty."},"q17":{"question":"Let L = L1∩L2, where L1 and L2 are languages as defined below:\nL1 = { | m, n >= 0 }\nL2 = { | i, j, k >= 0 }\nThen L is","hint":"None","answer_b":"Regular","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Not recursive","answer_d":"Recursively enumerable but not context free.","answer_c":"Context free but not regular"},"q39":{"question":"Consider the following problem X.\n\nGiven a Turing machine M over the input alphabet Σ, any\nstate q of M And a word w∈Σ*, does the computation of M\non w visit the state q? \nWhich of the following statements about X is correct?","hint":"None","answer_b":"X is undecidable but partially decidable","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"X is decidable","answer_d":"X is not a decision problem","answer_c":"X is undecidable and not even partially decidable"},"q16":{"question":"S -> aSa|bSb|a|b; The language generated by the above grammar over the alphabet {a,b} is the set of","hint":"None","answer_b":"All odd length palindromes.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"All palindromes","answer_d":"All even length palindromes","answer_c":"Strings that begin and end with the same symbol"},"q38":{"question":"Consider two languages L1 and L2 each on the alphabet ∑. Let f : ∑ → ∑ be a polynomial time computable bijection such that (∀ x) [x ∈ L1 iff f(x) ∈ L2]. Further, let f-1 be also polynomial time computable. Which of the following CANNOT be true?","hint":"None","answer_b":"L1 ∈ NP and L2 ∈ P","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"L1 ∈ P and L2 is finite","answer_d":"L1 is recursively enumerable and L2 is recursive","answer_c":"L1 is undecidable and L2 is decidable"},"q19":{"question":"Consider the CFG with {S,A,B) as the non-terminal alphabet, {a,b) as the terminal alphabet, S as the start symbol and the following set of production rules\nS --> aB        S --> bA\nB --> b         A --> a\nB --> bS        A --> aS\nB --> aBB       A --> bAA\nWhich of the following strings is generated by the grammar?","hint":"None","answer_b":"aabbbb","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"aaaabb","answer_d":"abbbba","answer_c":"aabbab"},"q18":{"question":"The language L= {0i21i | i≥0 } over the alphabet {0,1, 2} is:","hint":"None","answer_b":"is recursive and is a deterministic CFL.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"not recursive","answer_d":"is not a deterministic CFL but a CFL.","answer_c":"is a regular language."},"q1":{"question":"Consider the languages L1 = and L2 = {a}. Which one of the following represents L1 L2* U L1*","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q2":{"question":"Consider the DFA given. Which of the following are FALSE?\n\n1. Complement of L(A) is context-free.\n2. L(A) = L((11*0+0)(0 + 1)*0*1*)\n3. For the language accepted by A, A is the minimal DFA.\n4. A accepts all strings over {0, 1} of length at least 2. ","hint":"None","answer_b":"2 and 4 only","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"1 and 3 only","answer_d":"3 and 4 only","answer_c":"2 and 3 only"},"q3":{"question":"Given the language L = {ab, aa, baa}, which of the following strings are in L*?\n\n1) abaabaaabaa\n2) aaaabaaaa\n3) baaaaabaaaab\n4) baaaaabaa ","hint":"None","answer_b":"2, 3 and 4","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"1, 2 and 3","answer_d":"1, 3 and 4","answer_c":"1, 2 and 4"},"q4":{"question":"Given the language L = {ab, aa, baa}, which of the following strings are in L*?\n\n1) abaabaaabaa\n2) aaaabaaaa\n3) baaaaabaaaab\n4) baaaaabaa ","hint":"None","answer_b":"2, 3 and 4","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"1, 2 and 3","answer_d":"1, 3 and 4","answer_c":"1, 2 and 4"},"q5":{"question":"Consider the set of strings on {0,1} in which, every substring of 3 symbols has at most two zeros. For example, 001110 and 011001 are in the language, but 100010 is not. All strings of length less than 3 are also in the language. A partially completed DFA that accepts this language is shown below. The missing arcs in the DFA are","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q6":{"question":"Definition of a language L with alphabet {a} is given as following.\n\n             L={| k>0, and n is a positive integer constant}\nWhat is the minimum number of states needed in DFA to recognize L?","hint":"None","answer_b":"n+1","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"k+1","answer_d":"2^(k+1)","answer_c":"2^(n+1)"},"q7":{"question":"A deterministic finite automation (DFA)D with alphabet {a,b} is given below Which of the following finite state machines is a valid minimal DFA which accepts the same language as D?","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q8":{"question":"Let w be any string of length n is {0,1}*. Let L be the set of all substrings of w. What is the minimum number of states in a non-deterministic finite automaton that accepts L?","hint":"None","answer_b":"n","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"n-1","answer_d":"2n-1","answer_c":"n+1"},"q9":{"question":"Which one of the following languages over the alphabet {0,1} is described by the regular expression: (0+1)*0(0+1)*0(0+1)*?","hint":"None","answer_b":"The set of all strings containing at most two 0\u2019s.","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"The set of all strings containing the substring 00.","answer_d":"The set of all strings that begin and end with either 0 or 1.","answer_c":"The set of all strings containing at least two 0\u2019s."},"q40":{"question":"Consider the following decision problems:\n(P1) Does a given finite state machine accept a given string\n(P2) Does a given context free grammar generate an infinite \n     number of stings\nWhich of the following statements is true?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Neither (P1) nor (P2) are decidable","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Both (P1) and (P2) are decidable","answer_d":"Only (P2) is decidable","answer_c":"Only (P1) is decidable"},"q20":{"question":"For the correct answer strings to above question, how many derivation trees are there?","hint":"None","answer_b":"2","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"1","answer_d":"4","answer_c":"3"},"q22":{"question":"Let L1 be a recursive language. Let L2 and L3 be languages that are recursively enumerable but not recursive. Which of the following statements is not necessarily true? (A) L2 \u2013 L1 is recursively enumerable. (B) L1 \u2013 L3 is recursively enumerable (C) L2 ∩ L1 is recursively enumerable (D) L2 ∪ L1 is recursively enumerable","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q21":{"question":"Which of the following statements is/are FALSE?\n\n1. For every non-deterministic Turing machine, \n   there exists an equivalent deterministic Turing machine.\n2. Turing recognizable languages are closed under union \n   and complementation.\n3. Turing decidable languages are closed under intersection \n   and complementation.\n4. Turing recognizable languages are closed under union \n   and intersection. ","hint":"None","answer_b":"1 and 3 only","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"1 and 4 only","answer_d":"3 only","answer_c":"2 only"},"q24":{"question":"If L and L' are recursively enumerable, then L is","hint":"None","answer_b":"context-free","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"regular","answer_d":"recursive","answer_c":"context-sensitive"},"q23":{"question":"Which of the following is true for the language","hint":"None","answer_b":"It is regular but not context-free","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"It is not accepted by a Turing Machine","answer_d":"It is neither regular nor context-free, but accepted by a Turing machine","answer_c":"It is context-free but not regular"},"q26":{"question":"Let A ≤m B denotes that language A is mapping reducible (also known as many-to-one reducible) to language B. Which one of the following is FALSE? a)  If A ≤m B and B is recursive then A is recursive. b) If A ≤m B and A is undecidable then B is undecidable. c) If A ≤m B and B is recursively enumerable then A is recursively enumerable. d) If A ≤m B  and B is not recursively enumerable then A is not recursively enumerable.","hint":"None","answer_b":"b","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"a","answer_d":"d","answer_c":"c"},"q25":{"question":"Let L be a language and L' be its complement. Which one of the following is NOT a viable possibility?","hint":"None","answer_b":"One of L and L' is r.e. but not recursive; the other is not r.e.","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Neither L nor L' is recursively enumerable (r.e.).","answer_d":"Both L and L' are recursive","answer_c":"Both L and L' are r.e. but not recursive."},"q28":{"question":"Let L1 be a recursive language, and let L2 be a recursively enumerable but not a recursive language. Which one of the following is TRUE?\n\nL1' --> Complement of L1\nL2' --> Complement of L2 ","hint":"None","answer_b":"L1' is recursive and L2' is not recursively enumerable","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"L1' is recursive and L2' is recursively enumer­able","answer_d":"L1' is recursively enumerable and L2' is recursive","answer_c":"L1' and L2' are recursively enumerable"},"q27":{"question":"For S ∈ (0 + 1) * let d(s) denote the decimal value of s (e.g. d(101) = 5). Let L = {s ∈ (0 + 1)* d(s)mod5 = 2 and d(s)mod7 != 4}. Which one of the following statements is true?","hint":"None","answer_b":"L is recursive, but not context-free","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"L is recursively enumerable, but not recursive","answer_d":"L is regular","answer_c":"L is context-free, but not regular"},"q29":{"question":"L1 is a recursively enumerable language over Σ. An algorithm A effectively enumerates its words as w1, w2, w3, ... Define another language L2 over Σ Union {#} as {wi # wj : wi, wj ∈ L1, i < j}. Here # is a new symbol. Consider the following assertions.\n\nS1 :  L1 is recursive implies L2 is recursive\nS2 : L2 is recursive implies L1 is recursive \nWhich of the following statements is true ?","hint":"None","answer_b":"S1 is true but S2 is not necessarily true","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Both S1 and S2 are true","answer_d":"Neither is necessarily true","answer_c":"S2 is true but S1 is not necessarily true"}},"Database":{"q31":{"question":"Consider the following transactions with data items P and Q initialized to zero:\nT1: read (P) ;\n    read (Q) ;\n    if P = 0 then Q : = Q + 1 ;\n    write (Q) ;\nT2: read (Q) ;\n    read (P) ;\n    if Q = 0 then P : = P + 1 ;\n    write (P) ;\nAny non-serial interleaving of T1 and T2 for concurrent execution leads to","hint":"None","answer_b":"A schedule that is not conflict serializable","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"A serializable schedule","answer_d":"A schedule for which a precedence graph cannot be drawn","answer_c":"A conflict serializable schedule"},"q30":{"question":"Given the following schema:\n\n     employees(emp-id, first-name, last-name, hire-date, dept-id, salary)\n     departments(dept-id, dept-name, manager-id, location-id) \nYou want to display the last names and hire dates of all latest hires in their respective departments in the location ID 1700. You issue the following query:\n\nSQL> SELECT last-name, hire-date\n     FROM employees\n     WHERE (dept-id, hire-date) IN\n     (SELECT dept-id, MAX(hire-date)\n     FROM employees JOIN departments USING(dept-id)\n     WHERE location-id = 1700\n     GROUP BY dept-id); \nWhat is the outcome?","hint":"None","answer_b":"It executes and gives the correct result.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"It executes but does not give the correct result.","answer_d":"It generates an error because the GROUP BY clause cannot be used with table joins in a subquery","answer_c":"It generates an error because of pairwise comparison."},"q11":{"question":"Relation R has eight attributes ABCDEFGH. Fields of R contain only atomic values. F = {CH -> G, A -> BC, B -> CFH, E -> A, F -> EG} is a set of functional dependencies (FDs) so that F+ is exactly the set of FDs that hold for R. How many candidate keys does the relation R have?","hint":"None","answer_b":"4","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"3","answer_d":"6","answer_c":"5"},"q33":{"question":"Consider the following schedule for transactions T1, T2 and T3: Which one of the schedules below is the correct serialization of the above?","hint":"None","answer_b":"T2->>T1->>T3","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"T1->>T3->>T2","answer_d":"T3->>T1->>T2","answer_c":"T2->>T3->>T1"},"q10":{"question":"Information about a collection of students is given by the relation studinfo(studId, name, sex). The relation enroll(studId, courseId) gives which student has enrolled for (or taken) that course(s). Assume that every course is taken by at least one male and at least one female student. What does the following relational algebra expression represent?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Courses in which a proper subset of female students are enrolled.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Courses in which all the female students are enrolled.","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"Courses in which only male students are enrolled."},"q32":{"question":"Which of the following concurrency control protocols ensure both conflict serialzability and freedom from deadlock? I. 2-phase locking II. Time-stamp ordering","hint":"None","answer_b":"II only","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"I only","answer_d":"Neither I nor II","answer_c":"Both I and II"},"q13":{"question":"Which of the following is TRUE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"A relation R is in 3NF if every non-prime attribute of R is fully functionally dependent on every key of R","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Every relation in 3NF is also in BCNF","answer_d":"No relation can be in both BCNF and 3NF","answer_c":"Every relation in BCNF is also in 3NF"},"q35":{"question":"Consider the following schedule S of transactions T1, T2, T3, T4: Which one of the following statements is CORRECT?","hint":"None","answer_b":"S is not conflict-serializable but is recoverable","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"S is conflict-serializable but not recoverable","answer_d":"S is neither conflict-serializable nor is it recoverable","answer_c":"S is both conflict-serializable and recoverable"},"q12":{"question":"Consider the FDs given in above question. The relation R is","hint":"None","answer_b":"in 2NF, but not in 3NF.","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"in 1NF, but not in 2NF.","answer_d":"in BCNF","answer_c":"in 3NF, but not in BCNF."},"q34":{"question":"Consider the following four schedules due to three transactions (indicated by the subscript) using read and write on a data item x, denoted by r(x) and w(x) respectively. Which one of them is conflict serializable.","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q15":{"question":"Consider the following relational schema:\nSuppliers(sid:integer, sname:string, city:string, street:string)\nParts(pid:integer, pname:string, color:string)\nCatalog(sid:integer, pid:integer, cost:real)\nAssume that, in the suppliers relation above, each supplier and each street within a city has a unique name, and (sname, city) forms a candidate key. No other functional dependencies are implied other than those implied by primary and candidate keys. Which one of the following is TRUE about the above schema?","hint":"None","answer_b":"The schema is in 3NF but not in BCNF","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"The schema is in BCNF","answer_d":"The schema is not in 2NF","answer_c":"The schema is in 2NF but not in 3NF"},"q37":{"question":"Consider the following log sequence of two transactions on a bank account, with initial balance 12000, that transfer 2000 to a mortgage payment and then apply a 5% interest.\n\n  1. T1 start\n  2. T1 B old=12000 new=10000\n  3. T1 M old=0 new=2000\n  4. T1 commit\n  5. T2 start\n  6. T2 B old=10000 new=10500\n  7. T2 commit \nSuppose the database system cra shes just before log record 7 is written. When the system is restarted, which one statement is true of the recovery procedure?","hint":"None","answer_b":"We must undo log record 6 to set B to 10000 and then redo log records 2 and 3.","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"We must redo log record 6 to set B to 10500","answer_d":"We can apply redo and undo operations in arbitrary order because they are idempotent","answer_c":"We need not redo log records 2 and 3 because transaction T1 has committed."},"q14":{"question":"Consider a relational table with a single record for each registered student with the following attributes.\n\n1. Registration_Num: Unique registration number\n   of each registered student\n2. UID: Unique identity number, unique at the \n   national level for each citizen\n3. BankAccount_Num: Unique account number at\n   the bank. A student can have multiple accounts\n   or join accounts. This attribute stores the \n   primary account number.\n4. Name: Name of the student\n5. Hostel_Room: Room number of the hostel \nWhich one of the following option is INCORRECT?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Registration_Num can be a primary key","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"BankAccount_Num is candidate key","answer_d":"If S is a superkey such that S∩UID is NULL then S∪UID is also a superkey","answer_c":"UID is candidate key if all students are from the same country"},"q36":{"question":"Consider the transactions T1, T2, and T3 and the schedules S1 and S2 given below.\n\nT1: r1(X); r1(Z); w1(X); w1(Z)\nT2: r2(Y); r2(Z); w2(Z)\nT3: r3(Y); r3(X); w3(Y)\nS1: r1(X); r3(Y); r3(X); r2(Y); r2(Z);\n    w3(Y); w2(Z); r1(Z); w1(X); w1(Z)\nS2: r1(X); r3(Y); r2(Y); r3(X); r1(Z);\n    r2(Z); w3(Y); w1(X); w2(Z); w1(Z) \nWhich one of the following statements about the schedules is TRUE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Only S2 is conflict-serializable.","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Only S1 is conflict-serializable.","answer_d":"Neither S1 nor S2 is conflict-serializable.","answer_c":"Both S1 and S2 are conflict-serializable."},"q17":{"question":"Consider the relation scheme R = {E, F, G, H, I, J, K, L, M, M} and the set of functional dependencies {{E, F} -> {G}, {F} -> {I, J}, {E, H} -> {K, L}, K -> {M}, L -> {N} on R. What is the key for R?","hint":"None","answer_b":"{E, F, H}","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"{E, F}","answer_d":"{E}","answer_c":"{E, F, H, K, L}"},"q39":{"question":"Consider three data items D1, D2 and D3 and the following execution schedule of transactions T1, T2 and T3. In the diagram, R(D) and W(D) denote the actions reading and writing the data item D respectively. Which of the following statements is correct?","hint":"None","answer_b":"The schedule is serializable as T2; T1; T3","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"The schedule is serializable as T2; T3; T1","answer_d":"The schedule is not serializable","answer_c":"The schedule is serializable as T3; T2; T1"},"q16":{"question":"Consider the following relational schemes for a library database: Book (Title, Author, Catalog_no, Publisher, Year, Price) Collection (Title, Author, Catalog_no) with in the following functional dependencies:\n\nI. Title Author --> Catalog_no\nII. Catalog_no --> Title, Author, Publisher, Year\nIII. Publisher Title Year --> Price \nAssume {Author, Title} is the key for both schemes. Which of the following statements is true?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Both Book and Collection are in 3NF only","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Both Book and Collection are in BCNF","answer_d":"Both Book and Collection are in 2NF only","answer_c":"Book is in 2NF and Collection is in 3NF"},"q38":{"question":"Which of the following scenarios may lead to an irrecoverable error in a database system ?","hint":"None","answer_b":"A transaction reads a data item after it is read by an uncommitted transaction","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"A transaction writes a data item after it is read by an uncommitted transaction","answer_d":"A transaction reads a data item after it is written by an uncommitted transaction","answer_c":"A transaction reads a data item after it is written by a committed transaction"},"q19":{"question":"The maximum number of superkeys for the relation schema R(E,F,G,H) with E as the key is","hint":"None","answer_b":"6","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"5","answer_d":"8","answer_c":"7"},"q18":{"question":"Given the following two statements:\n\n  S1: Every table with two single-valued \n      attributes is in 1NF, 2NF, 3NF and BCNF.\n\n  S2: AB->C, D->E, E->C is a minimal cover for \n      the set of functional dependencies \n      AB->C, D->E, AB->E, E->C. \nWhich one of the following is CORRECT?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Both S1 and S2 are TRUE.","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"S1 is TRUE and S2 is FALSE.","answer_d":"Both S1 and S2 are FALSE.","answer_c":"S1 is FALSE and S2 is TRUE."},"q1":{"question":"Consider the following relational schema.\n\n    Students(rollno: integer, sname: string)\n    Courses(courseno: integer, cname: string)\n    Registration(rollno: integer, courseno: integer, percent: real)\nWhich of the following queries are equivalent to this query in English?\n      \"Find the distinct names of all students who score \n       more than 90% in the course numbered 107\"","hint":"None","answer_b":"I, II and III only","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"I, II, III and IV","answer_d":"II, III and IV only","answer_c":"I, II and IV only"},"q2":{"question":"Given the basic ER and relational models, which of the following is INCORRECT?","hint":"None","answer_b":"An attribute of an entity can be composite","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"An attribute of an entity can have more than one value","answer_d":"In a row of a relational table, an attribute can have exactly one value or a NULL value","answer_c":"In a row of a relational table, an attribute can have more than one value"},"q3":{"question":"Suppose (A, B) and (C,D) are two relation schemas. Let r1 and r2 be the corresponding relation instances. B is a foreign key that refers to C in r2. If data in r1 and r2 satisfy referential integrity constraints, which of the following is ALWAYS TRUE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"B","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"A","answer_d":"D","answer_c":"C"},"q4":{"question":"Consider the following relations A, B, C. How many tuples does the result of the following relational algebra expression contain? Assume that the schema of A U B is the same as that of A.\n\nTable A\nId   Name    Age\n----------------\n12   Arun    60\n15   Shreya  24\n99   Rohit   11\n\n\nTable B\nId   Name   Age\n----------------\n15   Shreya  24\n25   Hari    40\n98   Rohit   20\n99   Rohit   11\n\n\nTable C\nId   Phone  Area\n-----------------\n10   2200   02  \n99   2100   01","hint":"None","answer_b":"4","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"7","answer_d":"9","answer_c":"5"},"q5":{"question":"Consider a relational table r with sufficient number of records, having attributes A1, A2,\u2026, An and let 1 <= p <= n. Two queries Q1 and Q2 are given below. The database can be configured to do ordered indexing on Ap or hashing on Ap. Which of the following statements is TRUE?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Hashing will always outperform ordered indexing for both queries","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"Ordered indexing will always outperform hashing for both queries","answer_d":"Hashing will outperform ordered indexing on Q2, but not on Q1.","answer_c":"Hashing will outperform ordered indexing on Q1, but not on Q2"},"q6":{"question":"Which of the following tuple relational calculus expression(s) is/are equivalent to ","hint":"None","answer_b":"II only ","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"I only ","answer_d":"III and IV only ","answer_c":"III only "},"q7":{"question":"1) Let R and S be two relations with the following schema R (P,Q,R1,R2,R3) S (P,Q,S1,S2) Where {P, Q} is the key for both schemas. Which of the following queries are equivalent?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Only I and III","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Only I and II","answer_d":"Only I, III and IV","answer_c":"Only I, II and III"},"q8":{"question":"Consider the following ER diagram. The minimum number of tables needed to represent M, N, P, R1, R2 is","hint":"None","answer_b":"3","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"2","answer_d":"5","answer_c":"4"},"q9":{"question":"Consider the data given in above question. Which of the following is a correct attribute set for one of the tables for the correct answer to the above question?","hint":"None","answer_b":"{M1, P1, N1, N2}","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"{M1, M2, M3, P1}","answer_d":"{M1, P1}","answer_c":"{M1, P1, N1}"},"q40":{"question":"Consider the following transaction involving two bank accounts x and y.\n\nread(x);  x := x \u2013 50;  write(x);  read(y);  y := y + 50;  write(y) \nThe constraint that the sum of the accounts x and y should remain constant is that of","hint":"None","answer_b":"Consistency","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"Atomicity","answer_d":"Durability","answer_c":"Isolation"},"q20":{"question":"Given the STUDENTS relation as shown below. For (StudentName, StudentAge) to be the key for this instance, the value X should not be equal to","hint":"None","answer_b":"19","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"18","answer_d":"N/A","answer_c":"N/A"},"q22":{"question":"Table A\nId   Name    Age\n----------------\n12   Arun    60\n15   Shreya  24\n99   Rohit   11\n\n\nTable B\nId   Name   Age\n----------------\n15   Shreya  24\n25   Hari    40\n98   Rohit   20\n99   Rohit   11\n\n\nTable C\nId   Phone  Area\n-----------------\n10   2200   02  \n99   2100   01\nConsider the above tables A, B and C. How many tuples does the result of the following SQL query contains?\n\nSELECT A.id \nFROM   A \nWHERE  A.age > ALL (SELECT B.age \n                    FROM   B \n                    WHERE  B. name = \"arun\") ","hint":"None","answer_b":"3","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"4","answer_d":"1","answer_c":"0"},"q21":{"question":"Which of the following statements are TRUE about an SQL query? P : An SQL query can contain a HAVING clause even if it does not have a GROUP BY clause Q : An SQL query can contain a HAVING clause only if it has a GROUP BY clause R : All attributes used in the GROUP BY clause must appear in the SELECT clause S : Not all attributes used in the GROUP BY clause need to appear in the SELECT clause","hint":"None","answer_b":"P and S","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"P and R","answer_d":"Q and S","answer_c":"Q and R"},"q24":{"question":"Database table by name Loan_Records is given below.\nBorrower    Bank_Manager   Loan_Amount\n Ramesh      Sunderajan     10000.00\n Suresh      Ramgopal       5000.00\n Mahesh      Sunderajan     7000.00\nWhat is the output of the following SQL query?\nSELECT Count(*) \nFROM  ( (SELECT Borrower, Bank_Manager \n       FROM   Loan_Records) AS S \n        NATURAL JOIN (SELECT Bank_Manager, \n                             Loan_Amount \n                      FROM   Loan_Records) AS T );","hint":"None","answer_b":"9","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"3","answer_d":"6","answer_c":"5"},"q23":{"question":"Consider a database table T containing two columns X and Y each of type integer. After the creation of the table, one record (X=1, Y=1) is inserted in the table. Let MX and My denote the respective maximum values of X and Y among all records in the table at any point in time. Using MX and MY, new records are inserted in the table 128 times with X and Y values being MX+1, 2*MY+1 respectively. It may be noted that each time after the insertion, values of MX and MY change. What will be the output of the following SQL query after the steps mentioned above are carried out?\n\nSELECT Y FROM T WHERE X=7;","hint":"None","answer_b":"255","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"127","answer_d":"257","answer_c":"129"},"q26":{"question":"Let R and S be relational schemes such that R={a,b,c} and S={c}. Now consider the following queries on the database:\nIV) SELECT R.a, R.b\n       FROM R,S\n            WHERE R.c=S.c\nWhich of the above queries are equivalent?","hint":"None","answer_b":"I and III","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"I and II","answer_d":"III and IV","answer_c":"II and IV"},"q25":{"question":"A relational schema for a train reservation database is given below. Passenger (pid, pname, age) Reservation (pid, class, tid)\nTable: Passenger\npid   pname   age\n-----------------\n 0    Sachin   65\n 1    Rahul    66\n 2    Sourav   67\n 3    Anil     69\n\nTable : Reservation\npid  class  tid\n---------------\n 0    AC   8200\n 1    AC   8201\n 2    SC   8201\n 5    AC   8203\n 1    SC   8204\n 3    AC   8202\nWhat pids are returned by the following SQL query for the above instance of the tables?\nSLECT pid\nFROM Reservation ,\nWHERE class \u2018AC\u2019 AND\n    EXISTS (SELECT *\n       FROM Passenger\n       WHERE age > 65 AND\n       Passenger. pid = Reservation.pid)","hint":"None","answer_b":"1, 2","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"1, 0","answer_d":"1, 5","answer_c":"1, 3"},"q28":{"question":"Consider the table employee(empId, name, department, salary) and the two queries Q1 ,Q2 below. Assuming that department 5 has more than one employee, and we want to find the employees who get higher salary than anyone in the department 5, which one of the statements is TRUE for any arbitrary employee table?\n\nQ1 : Select e.empId\n     From employee e\n     Where not exists\n        (Select * From employee s where s.department = \u201c5\u201d and \n                                        s.salary >=e.salary)\nQ2 : Select e.empId\n     From employee e\n     Where e.salary > Any\n    (Select distinct salary From employee s Where s.department = \u201c5\u201d)","hint":"None","answer_b":"Q2 is the correct query","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Q1 is the correct query","answer_d":"Neither Q1 nor Q2 is the correct query","answer_c":"Both Q1 and Q2 produce the same answer."},"q27":{"question":"Consider the following relational schema:\nSuppliers(sid:integer, sname:string, city:string, street:string)\nParts(pid:integer, pname:string, color:string)\nCatalog(sid:integer, pid:integer, cost:real)\nConsider the following relational query on the above database:\nSELECT S.sname\n    FROM Suppliers S\n        WHERE S.sid NOT IN (SELECT C.sid\n                            FROM Catalog C\n                            WHERE C.pid NOT IN (SELECT P.pid  \n                                                FROM Parts P\n                                                WHERE P.color<> 'blue'))\nAssume that relations corresponding to the above schema are not empty. Which one of the following is the correct interpretation of the above query?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Find the names of all suppliers who have not supplied a non-blue part.","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Find the names of all suppliers who have supplied a non-blue part.","answer_d":"Find the names of all suppliers who have not supplied only blue parts.","answer_c":"Find the names of all suppliers who have supplied only blue parts."},"q29":{"question":"Given the following statements:\n\n    S1: A foreign key declaration can always \n        be replaced by an equivalent check\n        assertion in SQL.\n    S2: Given the table R(a,b,c) where a and\n        b together form the primary key, the \n        following is a valid table definition.\n        CREATE TABLE S (\n            a INTEGER,\n            d INTEGER,\n            e INTEGER,\n            PRIMARY KEY (d),\n            FOREIGN KEY (a) references R) \nWhich one of the following statements is CORRECT?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Both S1 and S2 are TRUE.","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"S1 is TRUE and S2 is FALSE.","answer_d":"Both S1 and S2 are FALSE.","answer_c":"S1 is FALSE and S2 is TRUE."}},"Custom":{"q1":{"question":"Which one is correct team name in NBA?","hint":"We the North","answer_b":"Toronto Raptors","correct_answer":"b","topic":"Basketball","answer_a":"Brooklyn Pets","answer_d":"Memphis Bearcubs","answer_c":"Los Angeles Slackers"},"q2":{"question":"What is the best-case time complexity of bubble sort?","hint":"started from the bottom","answer_b":"n*log(n)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"Algorithms","answer_a":"n^2","answer_d":"n","answer_c":"n*log(n)^2"},"q3":{"question":"Which of the following sorting algorithms has the lowest worst-case complexity?","hint":"don't merge into oncoming traffic","answer_b":"bubble sort","correct_answer":"a","topic":"Algorithms","answer_a":"merge sort","answer_d":"selection sort","answer_c":"quick sort"},"q4":{"question":"Which of the following is not a stable sorting algorithm in its typical implementation?","hint":"think fast","answer_b":"merge sort","correct_answer":"c","topic":"Algorithms","answer_a":"insertion sort","answer_d":"bubble sort","answer_c":"quick sort"},"q5":{"question":"Which one of the following in-place sorting algorithms needs the minimum number of swaps?","hint":"select an answer","answer_b":"selection sort","correct_answer":"b","topic":"Algorithms","answer_a":"quick sort","answer_d":"heap sort","answer_c":"insertion sort"},"q6":{"question":"Let T be a depth first search tree in an undirected graph G. Vertices u and n are leaves of this tree T. The degrees of both u and n in G are at least 2. which one of the following statements is true?","hint":"love thy neighbor","answer_b":"there must exist a vertex w whose removal disconnects u and n in G","correct_answer":"d","topic":"Algorithms","answer_a":"there must exist a vertex w adjacent to both u and n in G","answer_d":"there must exist a cycle in G containing u and all its neighbors in G","answer_c":"there must exist a cycle in G containing u and n"},"q7":{"question":"Let A1, A2, A3, and A4 be four matrices of dimensions 10 x 5, 5 x 20, 20 x 10, and 10 x 5, respectively. The minimum number of scalar multiplications required to find the product A1A2A3A4 using the basic matrix multiplication method is","hint":"one hundred quinceaneras","answer_b":"2000","correct_answer":"a","topic":"Algorithms","answer_a":"1500","answer_d":"100","answer_c":"500"},"q8":{"question":"Which one of the following is an application of the stack data structure?","hint":"go above the call of duty","answer_b":"the stock span problem","correct_answer":"d","topic":"Data Structures","answer_a":"managing function calls","answer_d":"all of the above","answer_c":"artithmetic expression evaluation"},"q9":{"question":"The best data structure to check whether an arithmetic expression has balanced parenthesis is a","hint":"the odds are stacked against you","answer_b":"list","correct_answer":"d","topic":"Data Structures","answer_a":"queue","answer_d":"stack","answer_c":"tree"},"q11":{"question":"A list of n strings, each of length n, is sorted into lexicographic order using the merge sort algorithm. The worst case running time of this computation is","hint":"you'll be sorry","answer_b":"O(n^2*log(n))","correct_answer":"b","topic":"Data Structures","answer_a":"O(n*log(n))","answer_d":"O(n^3)","answer_c":"O(n^2 + log(n))"},"q10":{"question":"To implement Dijkstra�s shortest path algorithm on unweighted graphs so that it runs in linear time, the data structure to be used is","hint":"right on cue","answer_b":"queue","correct_answer":"b","topic":"Data Structures","answer_a":"stack","answer_d":"heap","answer_c":"b-tree"},"q13":{"question":"Consider a binary max-heap implemented using an array. Which one of the following array represents a binary max-heap?","hint":"the most popular vitamin","answer_b":"25, 12, 13, 10, 16, 8, 14","correct_answer":"c","topic":"Data Structures","answer_a":"25, 12, 16, 13, 10, 8, 14","answer_d":"25, 14, 12, 13, 10, 8, 16","answer_c":"25, 14, 16, 13, 10, 8, 12"},"q12":{"question":"Suppose that we have numbers between 1 and 1,000 in a binary search tree and want to search for the number 364. Which of the following sequences could not be the sequence of nodes examined?","hint":"i'm feeling lucky","answer_b":"926, 203, 912, 241, 913, 246, 364","correct_answer":"b","topic":"Data Structures","answer_a":"925, 221, 912, 245, 899, 259, 363, 364","answer_d":"3, 253, 402, 399, 331, 345, 398, 364","answer_c":"3, 400, 388, 220, 267, 383, 382, 279, 364"}},"Python":{"q11":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\nprint '{0:.2}'.format(1.0 / 3)","hint":"None","answer_b":"0.33","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"0.333333","answer_d":"Error","answer_c":"0.333333:-2"},"q10":{"question":"What is the output of the expression : 3*1**3","hint":"None","answer_b":"9","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"27","answer_d":"1","answer_c":"3"},"q13":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\ni = 0\n  while i < 3:\n     print i\n     i += 1\n  else:\n     print 0\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"0 1 2 0","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"0 1 2 3 0","answer_d":"Error","answer_c":"0 1 2"},"q12":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\nprint '{0:-2%}'.format(1.0 / 3)","hint":"None","answer_b":"0.33%","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"0.33","answer_d":"33%","answer_c":"33.33%"},"q15":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\nprint 'cd'.partition('cd')","hint":"None","answer_b":"(\u201d)","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"(\u2018cd\u2019)","answer_d":"(\u201d, \u2018cd\u2019, \u201d)","answer_c":"(\u2018cd\u2019, \u201d, \u201d)"},"q14":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\ni = 0\nwhile i < 5:\n    print(i)\n    i += 1\n    if i == 3:\n        break\nelse:\n    print(0)\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"0 1 2","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"0 1 2 0","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"Error"},"q17":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\nprint 'abcefd'.replace('cd', '12')","hint":"None","answer_b":"abcefd","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"ab1ef2","answer_d":"ab12ed2","answer_c":"ab1efd"},"q16":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\nprint 'abef'.partition('cd')","hint":"None","answer_b":"(\u2018abef\u2019, \u2018cd\u2019, \u201d)","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"(\u2018abef\u2019)","answer_d":"Error","answer_c":"(\u2018abef\u2019, \u201d, \u201d)"},"q19":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\nprint \"Hello World\"[::-1]","hint":"None","answer_b":"Hello Worl","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"dlroW olleH","answer_d":"Error","answer_c":"d"},"q18":{"question":"What will be displayed by the following code?\n\ndef f(value, values):\n    v = 1\n    values[0] = 44\nt = 3\nv = [1, 2, 3]\nf(t, v)\nprint(t, v[0])","hint":"None","answer_b":"1 44","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"1 1","answer_d":"3 44","answer_c":"3 1"},"q1":{"question":"What is the output of the following code :\n\nprint 9//2","hint":"None","answer_b":"4.0","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"4.5","answer_d":"Error","answer_c":"4"},"q2":{"question":"Which function overloads the >> operator?","hint":"None","answer_b":"gt()","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"more()","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"ge()"},"q3":{"question":"Which operator is overloaded by the or() function?","hint":"None","answer_b":"|","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"||","answer_d":"/","answer_c":"//"},"q4":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\ni = 0\nwhile i < 3:\n       print i\n       i++\n       print i+1\n","hint":"None","answer_b":"0 1 2 3 4 5","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"0 2 1 3 2 4","answer_d":"1 0 2 4 3 5","answer_c":"Error"},"q5":{"question":"Which of these is not a core data type?","hint":"None","answer_b":"Dictionary","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"Lists","answer_d":"Class","answer_c":"Tuples"},"q6":{"question":"What data type is the object below ? L = [1, 23, \u2018hello\u2019, 1]","hint":"None","answer_b":"Dictionary","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"List","answer_d":"Array","answer_c":"Tuple"},"q7":{"question":"Which of the following function convert a string to a float in python?","hint":"None","answer_b":"long(x [,base] )","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"int(x [,base])","answer_d":"str(x)","answer_c":"float(x)"},"q8":{"question":"Which of the following statement(s) is TRUE?\n1. A hash function takes a message of arbitrary length and generates a fixed length code.\n2. A hash function takes a message of fixed length and generates a code of variable length.\n3. A hash function may give the same hash value for distinct messages.\n  ","hint":"None","answer_b":"II and III only","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"I only","answer_d":"II only","answer_c":"I and III only"},"q9":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\ndef myfunc(a):\n    a = a + 2\n        a = a * 2\n    return a\n\nprint myfunc(2)","hint":"None","answer_b":"16","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"8","answer_d":"Runtime Error","answer_c":"Indentation Error"},"q20":{"question":"Given a function that does not return any value, what value is shown when executed at the shell?","hint":"None","answer_b":"bool","correct_answer":"d","topic":"None","answer_a":"int","answer_d":"None","answer_c":"void"},"q22":{"question":"What is the output of the following program :\n\nprint 0.1 + 0.2 == 0.3","hint":"None","answer_b":"False","correct_answer":"b","topic":"None","answer_a":"True","answer_d":"Error","answer_c":"Machine dependent"},"q21":{"question":"Which module in Python supports regular expressions?","hint":"None","answer_b":"regex","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"re","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"pyregex"},"q24":{"question":"What does ~~~~~~5 evaluate to?","hint":"None","answer_b":"-11","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"+5","answer_d":"-5","answer_c":"+11"},"q23":{"question":"Which of the following is not a complex number?","hint":"None","answer_b":"k = complex(2, 3)","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"k = 2 + 3j","answer_d":"k = 2 + 3J","answer_c":"k = 2 + 3l"},"q26":{"question":"________ is a simple but incomplete version of a function.","hint":"None","answer_b":"Function","correct_answer":"a","topic":"None","answer_a":"Stub","answer_d":"A function developed using top-down approach","answer_c":"A function developed using bottom-up approach"},"q25":{"question":"Given a string s = \u201cWelcome\u201d, which of the following code is incorrect?","hint":"None","answer_b":"print s.lower()","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"print s[0]","answer_d":"print s.strip()","answer_c":"s[1] = \u2018r\u2019"},"q28":{"question":"Which of the following is correct about Python?","hint":"None","answer_b":"It can be easily integrated with C, C++, COM, ActiveX, CORBA, and Java","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"It supports automatic garbage collection.","answer_d":"None of the above","answer_c":"Both of the above"},"q27":{"question":"To start Python from the command prompt, use the command ______","hint":"None","answer_b":"go python","correct_answer":"c","topic":"None","answer_a":"execute python","answer_d":"run python","answer_c":"python"}}}